Eponyms

An annotated list of eponyms, edited by Harold Ellis, was first published in the 39th edition. That list has now been updated by Susan Standring. An appropriate reference has been cited when it has not proved possible to source biographical information.

Achilles tendon   the calcaneal tendon.

   Achilles, in Greek mythology, was slain by a wound in his vulnerable heel, inflicted by Paris in the Trojan War.

Adam’s apple   a protrusion in the front of the throat that is part of the larynx.

   According to the Old Testament, Adam was the first man.

Adamkiewicz, artery of   the largest anterior medullary feeder artery to the anterior spinal artery. It varies in level, arising from the lower (T9–11) posterior intercostal, the subcostal or, less frequently, the upper, lumbar (L1–2) arteries. Most often occurs on the left side.

   Albert Adamkiewicz (1850–1921), Professor of Pathology, University of Cracow, Poland.

Addison’s disease   a disease resulting from progressive destruction of the suprarenal gland with deficiency in the secretion of adrenocortical hormones.

   Thomas Addison (1795–1860), English physician.

Alcock’s canal   canalis pudendalis.

   Benjamin Alcock (1801–1833), British anatomist who published an article in 1836 on the iliac arteries.

Allen’s test   a test of sufficiency of the blood supply to the hand by compression and release of the ulnar and radial arteries, and observation of the colour change of the hand.

   EV Allen (1901–1961), Professor of Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota, USA.

Alport’s syndrome   a rare hereditary condition characterized by progressive renal failure.

   Arthur Cecil Alport (1880–1959), South African physician.

Alzheimer’s disease   the most common form of dementia, characterized at postmortem by neurofibrillary tangles and amyloid plaques.

   Alois Alzheimer (1864–1915), neurologist, Breslau, Poland.

Ammon’s horn   the hippocampus. Cornu Ammonis, or Ammon’s horn, describes the whorled, chambered shells of a fossil genus of Cephalopods. It also refers to the ram-shaped horns on the head of the Egyptian god Amun.

Andresen lines   structural lines within dentine, representing incremental lines that run more or less perpendicular to the direction of the tubules. They represent an incremental period of about 1week and are best visualized when longitudinal ground sections are viewed between crossed polars.

   Viggo Andresen (1870–1950), Norwegian orthodontist.

Angelman syndrome   a chromosome 15 disorder comprising microcephaly with mental and motor retardation, epilepsy, ataxic gait or complete inability to walk, muscle hypotonia, EEG abnormalities and peculiar facies marked by a protruding jaw and tongue, occipital depression and blue eyes.

   Harry Angelman (1915–1996), English paediatrician.

Apert’s syndrome   a complex of craniofacial abnormalities caused by premature craniosynostosis, usually of the coronal suture, leading to turribrachycephaly, associated with syndactyly and polydactyly.

   Eugène Charles Apert (1868–1940), French paediatrician.

Arantius, nodule of   a small nodule in the free border of the aortic valves.

   Julio Caesar Aranzio (Arantius) (1530–1589), pupil of Vesalius. Professor of Medicine and Surgery, Bologna, Italy.

Argyll Robertson pupil   a pupil that reacts to accommodation but not light. A highly specific sign in neurosyphilis but may also occur in other conditions such as sarcoidosis, multiple sclerosis, and, occasionally, diabetes mellitus.

   Douglas Moray Cooper Lamb Argyll Robertson (1837–1909), ophthalmic surgeon, Edinburgh, UK. Worked in Berlin, Germany, with the German ophthalmologist Albrecht von Graefe.

Arnold: Arnold’s bundle   frontopontine fibres;

innominate canal of   the canal in the petrous portion of the temporal bone that transmits the auricular branch of the vagus;

Arnold’s nerve   the auricular branch of the vagus.

   Friedrich Arnold (1803–1890), German anatomist.

Arnold–Chiari malformation   a congenital brainstem and cerebellar herniation through the foramen magnum.

   Julius Arnold (1835–1915), Professor of Pathology, Heidelberg, Germany; Hans Chiari (1851–1916), Austrian pathologist.

Auerbach’s plexus   the autonomic nervous plexus between the circular and longitudinal layers of muscle of the intestinal wall.

   Leopold Auerbach (1828–1897), Professor of Neuropathology, Breslau, Poland.

Axenfeld–Rieger syndrome   an autosomal dominant disorder characterized by bilateral abnormalities of the anterior segment of the eye in association with extraocular anomalies.

   Karl Theodor Paul Polykarpus Axenfeld (1867–1930), German ophthalmologist; Herwigh Rieger (1898–1986), Austrian ophthalmologist.

Babinski reflex, response, sign   an upgoing plantar response in pyramidal tract disturbances.

   Joseph Babinski (1857–1922), pupil of Charcot, neurologist, Hôpital Pitié, Paris, France.

Bachmann’s bundle   the intra-auricular bundle.

   Jean George Bachmann (1877–1959), German–American physiologist, Professor of Physiology, Atlanta College of Physicians and Surgeons 1910–1915, USA.

Baillarger, bands, lines, striae, stripe of   inner and outer white striations on the cerebral cortex.

   Jules Gabriel Baillarger (1815–1890), French neurologist and psychiatrist.

Bardet–Biedl syndrome   an autosomal recessive ciliopathy characterized by retinal dystrophy, obesity, postaxial polydactyly, renal dysfunction, learning difficulties and hypogonadism.

   Georges Louis Bardet (1885–1966), French physician;

   Artur Biedl (1869–1933), Hungarian pathologist and endocrinologist.

Barkow, ligament of   the anterior and posterior portions of the fibrous capsule of the elbow joint.

   Hans KL Barkow (1798–1873), German anatomist.

Barr body   the inactive X-chromatin mass in the nucleus of female cells.

   Murray Llewellyn Barr (1908–1995), Professor of Anatomy, University of Western Ontario, Canada.

Barrett’s oesophagus   abnormal columnar mucosa (Barrett’s mucosa) that covers a variable length of the distal oesophagus.

   Norman Rupert Barrett (1903–1979), consultant thoracic surgeon, Royal Brompton Hospital, London, UK.

Bartholin’s: ducts and gland   the sublingual salivary gland and its ducts;

glands   the greater vestibular glands on either side of the vaginal orifice.

   Casper Bartholin (1655–1738), Professor of Medicine, Anatomy and Physics, Copenhagen, Denmark.

Bartons’ adductor cord   a dense cord on the ulnar side of the little finger that runs from the medial edge of the insertion of abductor digiti minimi (Barton NJ 1984 Dupuytren’s disease arising from the abductor digiti minimi. J Hand Surg (Brit & Europ) 9:265–70).

Bassett’s ligament   an accessory anterior–inferior tibiofibular ligament that presents as a low-lying slip inserted so far distally on the fibula that it may cause irritation of the lateral aspect of the talus.

   Frank H. Bassett III (1928–2007), American orthopaedic surgeon.

Batson’s vertebral venous plexus   the valveless vertebral venous veins that communicate with the prostatic venous plexus and explain the readiness of carcinoma of the prostate to spread to the pelvic bones and vertebrae.

   Oscar Batson (1894–1979), Professor of Anatomy, University of Philadelphia, USA.

Battle’s sign   bruising over the mastoid process developing 2 or 3days after fracture of the posterior cranial fossa.

   William Battle (1855–1936), surgeon, St Thomas Hospital, London, UK.

Baxter’s nerve   the first branch of the lateral plantar nerve (Baxter DE, Thigpen CM 1989 Heel pain: operative results. Foot Ankle 5:16–25).

   Donald E Baxter, American orthopaedic surgeon.

Beahrs’ triangle   otherwise known as Riddle’s triangle, the triangle is delimited by the recurrent laryngeal nerve in the tracheo-oesophageal groove, the inferior thyroid artery and the common carotid artery.

   Oliver Howard Beahrs (1914–2006), American surgeon.

Bechterew, nucleus of   the nucleus centralis tegmenti superior.

   Vladimir M Bekhterev (Bechterew) (1857–1927), Russian neurologist.

Becker muscular dystrophy   muscular dystrophy of the pelvis girdle type.

   Peter Emil Becker (1908–2000), German human geneticist.

Beck’s triad   a combination of three symptoms that characterize cardiac tamponade: high central venous pressure, low arterial pressure and a small, quiet heart.

   Claude Schaeffer Beck (1894–1971), American surgeon.

Beckwith–Wiedemann syndrome   an overgrowth syndrome – main symptoms are gigantism, macroglossia and umbilical abnormalities in the newborn, enlarged liver and spleen, hyperplasia of the kidney, congenital abnormalities of the urinary tract, slight microcephaly, clonic seizures.

   John Bruce Beckwith (1933–), American paediatric pathologist; Hans-Rudolf Wiedemann (1915–2006), German paediatrician.

Beighton Scoring System   a system that measures joint hypermobility on a 9-point scale.

   Peter H Beighton (1934–), British medical geneticist.

Bell’s muscle   a band of muscular fibres forming a slight fold in the wall of the bladder, running from the uvula vesicae to the opening of the ureter on either side, and bounding the trigonum (Fuss FK 1992 Contribution to the trigone musculature in the case of ureteral duplication. J Urol 147:1363–4).

Bell’s: nerve   the long thoracic nerve;

palsy   paresis or paralysis, usually unilateral, of the facial muscles, caused by dysfunction of the facial nerve.

   Sir Charles Bell (1774–1842), surgeon, Middlesex Hospital, London, UK.

Bennett shift, movement   the lateral shift of the working mandibular condyle during a laterotrusive movement.

   Norman Bennett (1870–1947), British dentist.

Bergmann cells, glia   the glial cells of the cerebellum.

   Gottlieb Heinrich Bergmann (1781–1861), neurologist and anatomist, Medical Director, Hildersheim Asylum, Germany.

   Bernard–Horner syndrome:

   see Horner’s syndrome.

Bernoulli effect   the phenomenon in which fluid flowing through a tube of varying diameter travels fastest and exerts the largest lateral pressure at its narrowest point.

   Jakob Bernoulli (1654–1705), mathematician, Switzerland. Shares with Isaac Newton the invention of calculus.

Berrettini branch   a superficial connection between the median and ulnar nerves, apparently displayed in an anatomical plate by Pietro Berrettini di Cortona in 1741. Similar communications are said to be shown in a print from Charles Estienne dated 1545 (Berrettini P, Petrioli CR 1741 Tabulae Anatomicae. Rome: Typographia Antonii de Rubeis: 1–4).

Berry’s ligament   the thickened elastic bundle connecting the superior horn of the thyroid cartilage to the tip of the greater horn of the hyoid cartilage (synonyms: lateral thyrohyoid ligament; ligamentum thyrohyoideum laterale).

   Sir James Berry (1860–1946), Canadian surgeon.

Betz cells   large pyramidal cells of the cerebral cortex.

   Vladimir Aleksandrovich Betz (1834–1894), Professor of Anatomy, Kiev, Ukraine.

Bezold’s abscess   subperiosteal temporal bone abscess.

   Friedrich Bezold (1842–1908), otologist, Munich, Germany.

Bichat, buccal fat pad of   a variable, but usually considerable, amount of adipose tissue in the cheek. It is often encapsulated to form a biconcave mass, that is particularly evident in infants (the suctorial fat pad).

   Marie-François Xavier Bichat (1771–1802), Professor of Anatomy and physician, Hôtel Dieu, Paris, France.

Bielschowsky stain   a silver stain for nerve fibres.

   Max Bielschowsky (1869–1940), German neuropathologist.

Billroth, cords of   splenic cords found in the red pulp between the sinusoids.

   Christian Albert Theodor Billroth (1829–1894), German-Austrian surgeon, considered to be the founder of modern abdominal surgery.

Bill’s bar   a vertical crest that separates the superior fundus above the crista falciformis into anterior and posterior portions containing the facial nerve (and nervus intermedius) and the superior vestibular nerve, respectively. It is usually described as a thin layer of arachnoid tissue that may have an osseous medial component.

   William Fouts House (1923–2012), American otologist, physician and medical researcher. Developed and invented the cochlear implant.

Birbeck granules   small, cross-striated granules first reported in the Langerhans cells of the epidermis.

   Michael S Birbeck (1925–2005), cancer researcher, Institute of Cancer Research, London, UK.

Bland–White–Garland syndrome   an anomalous origin of the left coronary artery arising from the pulmonary artery (ALCAPA) – a rare, but serious, congenital anomaly. The first clinical description in conjunction with autopsy findings was given by Bland and colleagues in 1933 (Bland EF 1933 Congenital anomalies of the coronary arteries: report of an unusual case associated with cardiac hypertrophy. Am Heart J 8:787–801).

Blake’s pouch   a temporary outpouching of the posterior membranous area continuous with the fourth ventricle; its neck becomes the foramen of Magendie (Blake JA 1900 The roof and lateral recesses of the fourth ventricle, considered morphologically and embryologically. J Comp Neurol 10:79–108).

   Joseph A Blake (1864–1937), American physician.

Blaschko’s lines   a pattern of cutaneous mosaicism that can be observed in a range of congenital and acquired skin conditions.

   Alfred Blaschko (1858–1892), German dermatologist, Berlin, Germany.

Bloom’s syndrome   an inherited disorder characterized by short stature, sun-sensitive skin changes, an increased risk of cancer, and other health problems (Bloom D 1954 Congenital telangiectatic erythema resembling lupus erythematosus in dwarfs; probably a syndrome entity. AMA Am J Dis Child 88:754–8).

   David Bloom, American dermatologist.

Bochdalek, triangle of   when present, the lumbocostal triangle of Bochdalek represents a developmental defect resulting from an incomplete formation of the pleuroperitoneal membrane, located in the posterolateral respiratory diaphragm between the lumbar and costal parts, superior to the lateral arcuate ligament;

Bochdalek’s hernia   a congenital diaphragmatic hernia due to failure of closure of the pleuroperitoneal hiatus.

   Vincent Alexander Bochdalek (1801–1883), Czech anatomist.

Boerhaave’s syndrome   spontaneous rupture of the oesophagus, first described in 1723; the patient was Baron Jan von Wassenaer, Grand Admiral of the Dutch Fleet and Prefect of Rhineland.

   Herman Boerhaave (1668–1738), Dutch physician, anatomist, botanist, chemist and humanist.

Bolk’s ansiform lobules   formerly known as the superior and inferior semilunar lobules in the cerebellum.

   Lodewijk Bolk (1866–1930), Dutch anatomist.

Bowman’s: anterior limiting lamina, layer   the anterior elastic membrane of the cornea;

capsule   the sheath surrounding the renal glomerulus;

glands   glands in the olfactory mucosa.

space   the space between the two walls of Bowman’s capsule, also called the urinary space.

   Sir William Bowman (1816–1892), surgeon, Birmingham General Hospital, then Professor of Anatomy and Physiology, King’s College Hospital, London, UK.

Braille text   a system of writing consisting of raised dots and points, which can be interpreted by touch as letters of the alphabet.

   Louis Braille (1809–1852), French teacher of the blind.

Brissaud’s sulcus   the transverse parietal sulcus.

   Édouard Brissaud (1852–1909), French physician and pathologist.

Broca lesion   anteroinferior detachment of the glenoid labrum (Broca A, Hartman H 1890 Contribution à l’étude des luxations de l’épaule (luxations anciennes, luxations recidivantes). Bulletins de La Société Anatomique de Paris 5, serie IV, 312–36. June 1890).

   Auguste Broca (1859–1924), French orthopaedic surgeon.

Broca’s: area   the speech area of the cerebral cortex;

diagonal band   a fibre tract in the basal forebrain;

plis de passage moyen de Broca   Broca described several passages or bridges connecting the frontal and parietal lobes in the vicinity of the central sulcus. The pli de passage fronto-parietal moyen is an elevation in the floor of the central sulcus at its midpoint, constant and occasionally duplicated.

   Pierre Paul Broca (1824–1880), Professor of Clinical Surgery, Paris, France.

Brödel, bloodless line of   the line of division between the areas of kidney supplied by the anterior and posterior branches of the renal artery.

   Max Brödel (1870–1941), medical artist, Leipzig, Germany, then Director of Institute of Art as Applied to Medicine, Baltimore, USA.

Brodmann’s area 17, area 18   the primary visual cortex.

   Korbinian Brodmann (1868–1918), Professor of Anatomy, Tübingen, Germany.

Brown-Séquard syndrome   an incomplete spinal cord lesion, characterized by ipsilateral upper motor neurone paralysis and loss of proprioception, as well as contralateral loss of pain and temperature sensation.

   Charles E Brown-Séquard (1817–1894), French physiologist and neurologist.

Broyles ligament   the anterior commissure, commissural tendon. A band of fibrous tissue that extends from the vocal ligaments to the midline of the inner surface of the upper thyroid cartilage.

   Edwin N Broyles (1894–1977), American laryngologist.

Bruch’s choroidal basal lamina, membrane   the basal membrane of the choroid.

   Karl Wilhelm Ludwig Bruch (1819–1884), Professor of Anatomy at Basle, Switzerland, and then Giessen, Germany.

Brunner’s glands   duodenal glands lying deep to the muscularis mucosae.

   Johann Konrad Brunner (1653–1727), Professor of Anatomy successively at Heidelberg, Germany, and Strasbourg, France.

Buck’s fascia   the penile fascial sheath.

   Gordon Buck (1807–1877), surgeon, New York, USA.

Budd–Chiari syndrome   spontaneous thrombosis (complete or partial) of the hepatic veins, with or without additional inferior vena caval thrombosis.

   George Budd (1808–1882), Professor of Medicine, King’s College Hospital, London, UK; Hans Chiari (1851–1916), Austrian pathologist.

Budge (and Waller), ciliospinal centre of   neurones located in the intermediolateral cell columns of the spinal cord (C8–T2) that receive a pretectal input and project to the superior cervical ganglion, and are involved in controlling the operation of the ciliary muscle. Associated with a reflex identified by Augustus Volney Waller and Ludwig Julius Budge in 1852.

Buerger’s disease   thromboangiitis obliterans (an inflammatory vasculopathy).

   Leo Buerger (1879–1943), Austrian-born American physician and urologist.

Buford complex   a combination of an absent anterior superior labrum and a cord-like middle glenohumeral ligament (Williams MM, Snyder SJ, Buford D 1994 The Buford complex – the cordlike middle glenohumeral ligament and absent anterosuperior labrum complex: a normal anatomic capsulolabral variant. Arthroscopy 10:241–7).

   Don Buford Jr, American orthopaedic surgeon.

Büngner, bands of   columns of denervated Schwann cells

   Otto von Büngner (1858–1905), German surgeon. Studied in Dorpat, Estonia and Halle, Germany, from 1877 to 1883 as a student of Eduard von Wahl (1833–1890) and Richard von Volkmann (1830–1889).

Bunnell tightness test   tests the tightness of the intrinsic muscles of the hand. The metacarpophalangeal joint is held extended by the examiner and the proximal interphalangeal joint is passively flexed. An inability to flex the latter indicates that the intrinsic muscle is foreshortened.

   Sterling Bunnell, (1882–1957), American surgeon who is considered to be the ‘founding father’ of American hand surgery.

Burns, suprasternal space of   a slit-like interval between two layers of the deep investing fascia of the neck that are attached to the anterior and posterior borders of the manubrium. The space contains a small amount of areolar tissue, the lower parts of the anterior jugular veins and the jugular venous arch, the sternal heads of the sternocleidomastoid muscles and sometimes a lymph node.

   Allan Burns (1781–1813), Scottish anatomist.

Cajal: interstitial cells of   cells in the muscularis externa of the gut wall active as pacemakers in gut motility;

interstitial nucleus of   group of neurones lateral to the Edinger–Westphal nucleus and ventrolateral to the periaqueductal grey in the rostral part of the midbrain within the medial longitudinal fasciculus involved in the vestibulo-ocular response, smooth pursuit and optokinetic eye movements and vertical eye movement during saccades (Cajal, S Ramón Y 1911 Histologie du système nerveux de l’homme et des vertébrés. Paris: Maloine, pp. 263–266).

Cajal–Retzius cell   ‘CR cell’, a class of neurones with different morphotypes that express Reln in the MZ/layer I.

   Santiago Ramón y Cajal (1852–1934), Professor of Anatomy, Valencia, then Barcelona, then Professor of Histology and Morbid Anatomy, Madrid, Spain; Cajal shared the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine (1906) with Camillo Golgi for their work on the structure of the nervous system. Gustav Magnus Retzius (1842–1919), Professor of Anatomy, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden. Son of Andreas Adolf Retzius.

Caldwell–Luc procedure   an operation that involves opening the maxillary sinus by way of an incision into the supradental fossa opposite the premolar teeth, usually done to remove tooth roots or abnormal tissue.

   George W Caldwell (1867–1946), American physician, writer and painter; Henri Luc (1855–1925), French laryngologist.

Calleja, islands of   aggregations of very small, densely packed granule cell neurones located in the basal forebrain of most vertebrate species. They are found in all layers of the olfactory tubercle and between the tubercle and the ventral striatum.

   Julián Calleja y Sánchez (1836–1913), Spanish physician and anatomist.

Calot’s triangle   an isosceles triangle based on the common hepatic duct with the cystic artery and cystic duct forming its sides.

   Jean-François Calot (1861–1914), surgeon, Rothschild Hospital, Berck-sur-Mer, France. Specialized in the treatment of surgical tuberculosis in children.

Campbell’s lines   five lines that should be traced when assessing a coronal radiograph of the facial skeleton (McGrigor B, Campbell W 1950 The radiology of war injuries. IV. Wounds of the face and jaw. Br J Radiol 23:685–96).

Camper’s: angle   the line running from the inferior border of the ala of the nose to the superior border of the tragus of the ear;

chiasm(a)   the passage of the tendons of flexor digitorum profundus (flexor digitorum longus in the foot) through the interval left by the decussation of the fibres of the tendons of flexor digitorum superficialis (flexor digitorum brevis in the foot);

fascia   the layer of fascia extending between the ischiopubic rami inferior to sphincter urethrae and the deep transverse perineal muscle;

plane   a plane defined by the inferior border of the right or left ala of the nose and the superior border of the tragus of both ears.

   Petrus Camper (1722–1789), Dutch physician and anatomist.

Cantlie’s line   a line that separates the right and left lobes of the liver, drawn from the inferior vena cava to just left of the gallbladder fossa.

   Sir James Cantlie (1851–1926), Scottish physician, a pioneer of First Aid, and co-founder of the Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese (subsequently, the University of Hong Kong).

Cantrell, pentalogy of   a syndrome of congenital defects involving the abdominal wall, sternum, diaphragm, pericardium and heart (Cantrell JR, Haller JA, Ravitch MM 1958 A syndrome of congenital defects involving the abdominal wall, sternum, diaphragm, pericardium, and heart. Surg Gynecol Obstet 107:602–14).

Carabelli’s cusp, cusplet, tubercle   an occasional fifth tubercle lingual to the anteromedial cusp of the first upper molar tooth.

   Edler Carabelli (1787–1842), Professor of Dental Surgery, Vienna, Austria.

Carnegie stage   not an eponym but a standardized system of 23 stages used to provide a unified developmental chronology of the vertebrate embryo.

   Carnegie Institution for Science, organization established to support scientific research, Washington, DC, USA.

Carpenter’s syndrome   mental retardation, acrocephaly and syndactyly related to, but genetically distinct from, Alpert’s syndrome.

   George Carpenter (1859–1910), physician, UK.

Carus, curve of   the lower end of the pelvic curve.

   Karl (Carl) Gustav Carus (1789–1869), German anatomist, physiologist and painter.

Chamberlain procedure   anterior mediastinotomy.

   J Maxwell Chamberlain (1906–1968), American thoracic surgeon.

Charcot’s artery of cerebral haemorrhage   the lenticulostriate branch of the middle cerebral artery.

   Jean-Martin Charcot (1825–1893), neurologist and physician, Salpêtrière, Paris, France.

Charcot–Marie–Tooth disease   an inherited disorder of nerves that is characterized by loss of muscle tissue and touch sensation, predominantly in the feet and legs.

   Jean-Martin Charcot (1825–1893), French neurologist and physician, Salpêtrière, Paris, France; Pierre Marie (1853–1940), French neurologist, assistant to Charcot; Howard Henry Tooth (1856–1925), British neurologist.

Chassaignac’s carotid tubercle   the prominent anterior tubercle of the transverse process of the sixth cervical vertebra, against which the carotid artery can be compressed.

   Charles-Marie Édouard Chassaignac (1805–1879), surgeon, Paris, France.

Cheyne–Stokes respiration   breathing pattern characterized by alternating periods of apnoea and hyperpnoea.

   John Cheyne (1777–1836), Scottish physician; William Stokes (1804–1878), Irish physician, Regius Professor of Physic at the University of Dublin.

   Chiari malformation, Chiari’s network:

   see Arnold–Chiari malformation.

   Hans Chiari (1851–1916), Austrian pathologist.

Chilaiditi’s syndrome   the presence of a long mesentery related to the distal ascending and proximal transverse colon, resulting in the presence of either or both becoming interposed between the right lobe of the liver and the diaphragm, with or without abdominal symptoms.

   Demetrius Chilaiditi (1883–1975), Greek radiologist in Vienna, Austria.

Chopart: joint   the transverse tarsal joint or midtarsal joint formed by the calcaneocuboid and talonavicular joints;

Chopart’s ligament   the bifurcate ligament (calcaneonavicular ligament and calcaneocuboid ligament).

   François Chopart (1743–1795), French surgeon. Professor of Practical Surgery at the École Pratique, Paris, France, from 1771; in 1782, he succeeded Toussaint Bordenave (1728–1782) as Chair of Physiology.

Clara cells   bronchiolar cells secreting surfactant. This is now regarded as a ‘tainted eponym’. Max Clara acknowledged that the sample on which he based his work ‘was obtained from a prisoner executed by the Nazi justice system’.

   Max Clara (1899–1966), Professor of Anatomy, Leipzig, Germany.

Clarke’s column   the basal nucleus in the posterior horn of spinal grey matter.

   Jacob Augustus Lockhart Clarke (1817–1880), neurologist, Hospital for Epilepsy and Paralysis, London, UK.

Claudius’ cells   supporting cells on the floor of the cochlear canal of the inner ear.

   Friedrich Matthias Claudius (1822–1869), Professor of Anatomy successively in Kiel and Marburg, Germany.

Cleland’s ligament, transverse retrovascular ligament   thin fibres passing from the lateral surfaces of the interphalangeal joints to the skin of the fingers.

   John Cleland (1835–1925), Professor of Anatomy, Glasgow, UK.

Cloquet’s node, gland   a lymph node in the femoral canal.

   Jules-Germain Cloquet (1790–1883), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Paris, France.

Colles’: fascia   a continuation of Scarpa’s layer of abdominal fascia;

fracture   a fracture of the lower end of the radius with dorsal displacement.

   Abraham Colles (1773–1843), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland, Dublin, Ireland.

Conn syndrome   a disorder of excessive aldosterone production.

   Jerome W Conn (1907–1994), American endocrinologist.

Cooper’s: pectineal ligament   thickened periosteum on the pecten pubis;

suspensory ligaments   suspensory ligaments of the breast.

   Sir Astley Pastor Cooper (1768–1841), surgeon, Guy’s Hospital, London, UK.

Corti: organ of, rods of   auditory hair cells of the cochlea;

tunnel of   the tunnel between the internal and external pillar cells in the inner ear.

   Alfonso Corti (1822–1888), histologist. Held no academic post but worked in Vienna, Austria; Berlin, Germany; Utrecht, Netherlands; and Turin, Italy.

Cowper’s glands   the bulbo-urethral glands.

   William Cowper (1666–1709), British surgeon and anatomist.

Crouzon’s syndrome   craniofacial dysostosis. Premature closures of cranial vault sutures, maxillary hypoplasia and ocular and aural anomalies.

   Octave Crouzon (1874–1938), neurologist, Salpêtrière, Paris, France.

Cullen’s sign   bluish discoloration at the umbilicus from extravasated blood in ruptured ectopic pregnancy and pancreatitis – an uncommon physical sign.

   Thomas Cullen (1869–1953), Professor of Gynaecology, Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, USA.

Cunningham, sulcus precentralis medialis of   the medial precentral sulcus in the cerebral cortex.

   Daniel John Cunningham (1850–1909), Scottish anatomist.

Cupid’s bow   the upper curl of the lip, which resembles Cupid’s bow.

   Cupid, the Roman god of love, pictured as a winged boy with a bow.

Cusco’s speculum   a bivalved, self-retaining speculum used to inspect the cervix.

   Edward Gabriel Cusco (1819–1894), French surgeon.

Cushing’s syndrome   the syndrome produced by glucocorticosteroid excess.

   Harvey Cushing (1869–1939), Professor of Surgery, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts; neurosurgeon, Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston, USA.

Cuvier, duct of   the termination of the cardinal vein in the fetus.

   Baron Georges Cuvier (1760–1832), zoologist and palaeontologist, Paris, France.

Dandy–Walker malformation   a variant of Arnold–Chiari syndrome involving the fourth ventricle and cerebellum.

   Walter Edward Dandy (1886–1946), American neurosurgeon, pioneer in surgery of the posterior skull cavity and intracranial vascular surgery; Arthur Earl Walker (1907–1995), American neurologist.

Danon disease   a condition characterized by cardiomyopathy, myopathy and intellectual disability; attributed to mutations in the LAMP2 gene (Danon MJ, Oh SJ, DiMauro S et al 1981 Lysosomal glycogen storage disease with normal acid maltase. Neurology 31:51–7).

Darkschewitsch, nucleus of   the posterior commissural nucleus.

   Liverij Osipovich Darkschewitsch (1858–1925), neuroanatomist, University of Moscow, Russia.

Darwin’s tubercle   a slight projection that may be present on the posterior superior aspect of the helix of the pinna (auricle) of the external ear.

   Charles Robert Darwin (1809–1882), English naturalist, author of On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection.

DeBakey classification   a system used to classify aortic dissections based upon the site of origin of the dissection. Dissections that include the aorta proximal to the left subclavian artery, with or without distal extension, are classified as type I or II. Dissections distal to the left subclavian artery are classified as type IIIa (extend to the respiratory diaphragm) or IIIb (extend below the respiratory diaphragm).

   Michael Ellis DeBakey (1908–2008), American cardiovascular surgeon and pioneer in surgical procedures for treatment of defects and diseases of the cardiovascular system.

Deiters’: nucleus   the lateral vestibular nucleus of the vestibulocochlear nerve;

phalangeal supporting cells   outer hair cells in the organ of Corti.

   Otto Friedrich Karl Deiters (1834–1863), Professor of Anatomy and Histology, Bonn, Germany.

Delphian node   prelaryngeal (anterior to larynx) lymph node(s), located just above the thyroid isthmus. They may harbour metastatic disease and should be routinely removed as part of a central neck dissection.

   Greek Oracle of Delphi, who could predict the future, because the presence of metastatic disease in these lymph nodes predicted that further nodal disease was present in the neck and that the patient had a worse cancer prognosis.

Denonvilliers’ fascia   the fascia separating the prostate from the rectum.

   Charles-Pierre Denonvilliers (1808–1872), Professor of Anatomy, Paris, France.

de Quervain’s tenovaginitis, tenosynovitis   stenosing tenovaginitis of the tendon sheath of abductor pollicis longus and extensor pollicis brevis.

   Fritz de Quervain (1868–1940), Professor of Surgery, Berne, Switzerland.

Descemet’s posterior limiting lamina, layer, membrane   the posterior membrane of the cornea.

   Jean Descemet (1732–1810), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Paris, France.

Dieulafoy lesion   rare cause of recurrent gastrointestinal bleeding from ectatic submucosal vessels in the intestinal mucosa.

   Paul Georges Dieulafoy (1839–1911), French physician.

DiGeorge syndrome   a congenital disorder in which defective development of the third and fourth pharyngeal pouches results in hypoplasia or aplasia of the thymus and parathyroid glands.

   Angelo Mario DiGeorge (1921–2009), American paediatrician.

Dingman approach   a popular method for repairing zygomatic complex fractures (Dingman RO, Natvig P 1964 Surgery of Facial Fractures. Philadelphia: WB Saunders).

Disse, perisinusoidal space of   the space between the venous sinusoid and the hepatic cells.

   Josef Disse (1852–1912), German anatomist.

Doppler effect   a change in frequency of an incident sound (or light) wave related to the difference in velocity between the sender and receiver (Doppler CA 1843 Über das farbige Licht der Doppelsterne und einiger anderer Gestirne des Himmels. Abh Königl Böhm Ges Wiss 2:465–82).

   Christian Andreas Doppler (1803–1853), Austrian mathematician and physicist.

Dorello’s canal   the invagination of the dura in the petroclival region from the petroclival entrance point to the posterior end of the cavernous sinus. It conveys the mid portion of the abducens nerve.

   Primo Dorello, Italian anatomist is credited with the discovery of the canal that bears his name in 1905, although it had been described in 1859 by Wenzel Leopold Gruber. Dorello was Professor of Human Anatomy at Peruggia (1926–1946).

Douglas: arcuate line of   the arcuate line of the sheath of rectus abdominis;

pouch of   the rectouterine peritoneal pouch.

   James Douglas (1675–1742), anatomist and obstetrician, London, UK.

Down’s syndrome   trisomy 21, producing mental retardation and a characteristic facies with variable additional abnormalities.

   John Langdon Haydon Down (1828–1896), Cornish physician, UK.

Drummond, marginal artery of, arch of   the anastomoses between the ileocolic, right colic, middle colic, left colic and sigmoid arteries (the arc of Riolan is the part of this arch between the middle and left colic artery).

   Hamilton Drummond (1882–1925), surgeon, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.

Duchenne muscular dystrophy   chronic progressive muscular atrophy due to mutations in the dystrophin gene.

   Guillaume Benjamin Amand Duchenne de Boulogne (1806–1875), French neurologist.

Dunbar syndrome   external compression of the coeliac trunk by the median arcuate ligament. The symptoms include abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting (aka median arcuate ligament syndrome (MALS), coeliac artery compression syndrome, coeliac axis syndrome, coeliac trunk compression syndrome, Harjola–Marable syndrome, Marable syndrome) (Dunbar JD, Molnar W, Beman FF, Marable SA 1965 Compression of the celiac trunk and abdominal angina. Am J Roentgenol Radium Ther Nucl Med 95:731–44).

Dupuytren’s disease, contracture   contraction and fibrosis of the palmar (and, occasionally, the plantar) fascia.

   Baron Guillaume Dupuytren (1777–1835), surgeon, Hôtel Dieu, Paris, France.

Eagle’s syndrome   an elongated and/or calcified styloid process and/or a calcified stylohyoid ligament impinge on local structures, triggering sudden sharp pain, e.g. when swallowing.

   Watt Weems Eagle (1898–1980), American otorhinolaryngologist.

Eberstaller: sulcus precentralis medialis of, diagonal sulcus of   (Eberstaller, O 1884 Zür Oberflachen Anatomie der Grosshirn Hemisphären. Vienna: Med. 7. Eberstaller O 1890 Das Stirnhirn. Vienna: Urban & Schwartzenberg).

Ebstein malformation   a rare congenital cardiac malformation where the septal and inferior tricuspid valve leaflets are attached abnormally deep into the right ventricular chamber.

   Wilhelm Ebstein (1836–1912), German physician.

Ecker: gyrus descendens of   a gyrus that encircles the retrocalcarine sulcus;

paracentral lobule of   a division of the medial aspect of the cerebral cortex formed by the anterior and the posterior paracentral gyri. It lies above the cingulate sulcus and is bounded by the paracentral sulcus anteriorly and the marginal part of the cingulate sulcus posteriorly.

   Johann Alexander Ecker (1816–1887), German anthropologist and anatomist.

Edinger–Westphal nucleus   the midbrain nucleus containing preganglionic neurones destined to synapse in the ciliary ganglion; it lies close to the nucleus of the oculomotor nerve.

   Ludwig Edinger (1855–1918), Professor of Anatomy, Frankfurt-am-Main, German; Karl Westphal (1833–1890), Professor of Psychiatry, Berlin, Germany.

Ehlers–Danlos syndrome   a group of rare genetic disorders affecting humans and domestic animals, caused by a defect in collagen synthesis.

   Edward Ehlers of Denmark (1863–1937) and Henri-Alexandre Danlos of France (1844–1912) identified the syndrome at the turn of the twentieth century.

Eisenmenger complex   the combination of ventricular septal defect with pulmonary hypertension and consequent right-to-left shunt through the defect, with or without an associated overriding aorta.

   Victor Eisenmenger (1864–1932), German physician.

Elliot Smith, paramesial sulcus of   paramesial sulcus, certebral cortex.

   Sir Grafton Elliot Smith (1871–1937), Australian anatomist.

Ellis–van Creveld syndrome   a very rare autosomal recessive skeletal dysplasia, with inter- and intra-familial variability, characterized by short ribs, short limbs, postaxial polydactyly, and dysplastic teeth and nails. Congenital heart defects occur in 60% of the individuals (Ellis RWB, van Crefeld S 1940 A syndrome characterized by ectodermal dysplasia, polydactyly, chondro-dysplasia and congenital morbus cardis. Arch Dis Child 15:65–84).

Elschnig’s layer   the astroglial membrane at the optic nerve head, continuous with the internal limiting membrane of the retina.

   Anton Elschnig (1863–1939), Professor, University of Prague Eye Clinic, Czech Republic.

Emery–Dreifuss muscular dystrophy   an X-linked form of muscular dystrophy (Emery AE, Dreifuss FE 1966 Unusual type of benign X-linked muscular dystrophy. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatr 29:338–42).

Epley’s manoeuvre   canalith repositioning for benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (Epley JM 1980 New dimensions of benign paroxysmal positional vertigo. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 88:599–605).

Erb’s point   a point on the side of the neck 2–3 cm above the clavicle and in front of the transverse process of the sixth cervical vertebra. Pressure over this point elicits Duchenne–Erb paralysis, and electrical stimulation over this area causes various arm muscles to contract.

   Wilhelm Erb (1840–1921), Professor of Neurology, Heidelberg, Germany.

Erb–Duchenne paralysis   the result of injury to the C5 and C6 roots of the brachial plexus.

   Wilhelm Erb (1840–1921), Professor of Neurology, Heidelberg, Germany; Guillaume Benjamin Amand Duchenne de Boulogne (1806–1875), French neurologist.

Essex–Lopresti injury   fractures of the radial head with distal radio-ulnar dislocation (Essex-Lopresti P 1951 Fractures of the radial head with distal radio-ulnar dislocation: report of two cases. J Bone Joint Surg Br 33:244–247).

Eustachian: tube   the pharyngotympanic tube;

valve   the inferior vena caval valve in the right atrium.

   Bartolomeo Eustachi (1513–1574), Professor of Anatomy, Rome, Italy, and physician to the Pope.

Fallopian: aqueduct, canal   the canal for the facial nerve in the temporal bone;

tube   the uterine tube.

   Gabrielle Fallopio (1523–1562), Professor of Anatomy, Padua, Italy. A pupil of Vesalius.

Fallot’s tetralogy   a congenital heart disease comprising pulmonary stenosis, right ventricular hypertrophy, ventricular septal defect and overriding of the aorta.

   Étienne-Louis Fallot (1850–1911), Professor of Medicine, Marseilles, France.

Fañanas cells   astroglial subtypes in the deeper molecular layer of the cerebellum (Fañanas JRY 1916 Contribucion al estudo de la neuroglia del cerebelo. Trab Lab Invest Biol (Madrid) 14:163–179).

   Jorge Ramon y Cajal Fananas (1886–?) Spanish physician.

Ferguson reflex   enhancement of uterine activity due to mechanical stretching of the lower uterine segment and cervix (Ferguson JKW 1941 A study of the motility of the intact uterus at term. Surg Gynecol Obstet 73:359–66).

   James Ferguson, Canadian obstetrician.

Fitz-Hugh–Curtis syndrome   a rare complication of pelvic inflammatory disease involving the liver capsule and leading to the creation of adhesions. Thomas Fitz-Hugh, Jr and Arthur Hale Curtis first reported this condition in 1934 and 1930, respectively.

   Arthur Hale ‘Art’ Curtis (1881–1955), American football player, coach and gynaecologist.

   Thomas Fitz-Hugh (1894–1963), American haematologist.

   Fleschig’s temporal knee:

   see Meyer’s loop.

Fordyce spots   small mucosal cysts of the cheeks, lips and tongue.

   John Addison Fordyce (1858–1925), dermatologist, New York, USA.

Forel, H field of   ventral tegmental decussation between the red nuclei.

   August Forel (1848–1931), anatomist and neurologist, Zurich, Switzerland.

Foville, quadrangular lobule of   the precuneus (part of the medial portion of the parietal lobe), delineated anteriorly by the marginal branch of the cingulate sulcus, posteriorly by the parieto-occipital sulcus, and inferiorly by multiple Y-shaped sulcal segments that constitute the subparietal sulcus.

   Achille Louis François Foville (1799–1878), French neurologist.

Fox’s sign   ecchymosis of the inguinal ligament due to blood tracking from the retroperitoneum and collecting at the inguinal ligament in haemorrhagic pancreatitis.

   George Henry Fox (1846–1937), American dermatologist.

Fox–Fordyce disease   a chronic, papular disease involving apocrine sweat duct obstruction, e.g. in the axilla.

   George Henry Fox (1846–1937), American dermatologist; John Addison Fordyce (1858–1925), American dermatologist (see Fordyce spots).

Freiberg’s infraction   osteochondrosis of a metatarsal head, usually the second (more rarely, third or fourth) metatarsal bone of the foot, presenting the picture of subchondral cancellous bone necrosis. Characterized by localized pain and swelling over the metatarsal head, red overlying skin and limitation of movement in an adolescent. X-rays show the head to be crushed and fragmented.

   Albert Henry Freiberg (1868–1940), American surgeon.

Frey’s syndrome   sweating in the distribution of the auriculotemporal nerve, triggered by eating (‘auriculo-gustatory sweating’) after injury to the facial nerve.

   Lucja Frey (1889–1944), neurologist, Warsaw, Poland.

Frohse (Fröhse), arcade of   an arcade between the two layers of supinator, that transmits the posterior interosseous nerve.

   Fritz Frohse (1871–1916), German anatomist.

Fröhlich’s syndrome   adiposogenital dystrophy.

   Alfred Fröhlich (1871–1953), Austrian pharmacologist in the USA.

Froment’s sign   weakness of adductor pollicis and the first dorsal interosseous substantially degrades pinch strength. Froment’s sign is positive when a slip of paper is held in the key pinch position between the pulp of the thumb and the radial side of the index proximal interphalangeal joint, and the tip of the thumb involuntarily flexes as flexor pollicis longus contracts to compensate for the absent adductor pollicis and first dorsal interosseous.

   Jules Froment (1878–1946), French neurologist.

Fruchaud, myopectineal orifice of   the surgical name given to the inferomedial aspect of the anterior abdominal wall.

   Henri Rene Fruchaud (1894–1960), Professor of Clinical Surgery, Angers.

Fuchs, crypts of   large depressions often found on the anterior surface of the iris.

   Ernst Fuchs (1851–1930), Austrian ophthalmologist.

Furnas’ ligament   retaining ligaments of the cheek (Furnas DW 1989 The retaining ligaments of the cheek. Plast Reconstr Surg 83:11–16).

   Futcher’s lines:

   see Voigt’s lines.

Galeazzi fracture-dislocation   a fracture of the distal part of the radius with dislocation of distal radio-ulnar joint and an intact ulna.

   Riccardo Galeazzi (1866–1952), Italian orthopaedic surgeon.

Galen’s: nerve, anastomosis (ansa galeni)   the anastomosis between the internal branch of the superior laryngeal nerve and the recurrent laryngeal nerve in the wall of the laryngopharynx;

vein (deep galenic venous system)   the great cerebral vein.

   Claudius Galen (130–200 AD), born Pergamum, Asia Minor, studied there and in Smyrna, Corinth and Alexandria. Physician to Marcus Aurelius and teacher of anatomy and medicine in Rome. Author of numerous texts on anatomy, surgery and medicine.

Gans, fissure of   a structure that lies on the undersurface of the right lobe of the liver behind the gallbladder fossa; it often marks the variable site of division of the portal pedicle to the right posterior sector.

   Henry Gans (1925–2017), Dutch surgeon.

Gartner’s: cyst   usually a benign cyst in the anterolateral wall of the vaginal remnant of Gartner’s duct;

duct   the paravaginal duct; a mesonephric duct remnant.

   Hermann Treschow Gartner (1785–1827), surgeon in the Norwegian and then Danish armies.

Gasserian ganglion   sensory ganglion of the trigeminal nerve. The ganglion was described in 1765 by Antonius Hirsh, who named it after his teacher.

   Johann Lorentz Gasser (1723–1765), Austrian anatomist.

Gennari, stria of, white line of   a white band or stripe in the occipital cortex.

   Francesco Gennari (1750–1797), anatomist, Parma, Italy.

Gerdy’s tubercle   the attachment of the iliotibial tract to the proximal tibia.

   Pierre Nicolas Gerdy (1797–1856), surgeon and pathologist, Paris, France.

Gerota’s fascia   the renal fascia, which encapsulates the perinephric fat.

   Dumitru Gerota (1867–1939), Professor of Surgery, Bucharest, Romania.

Geschwind’s area/territory/region   a region in the inferior parietal lobule.

   Norman Geschwind (1926–1984), American behavioural neurologist.

Giacomini, band of   the band on the surface of the uncus.

   Carlo Giacomini (1840–1898), Professor of Anatomy, Turin, Italy.

Giemsa staining   a solution containing azure-II, glycerin and methanol. Stained elements appear pink, purple or blue.

   Gustav Giemsa (1867–1948), German chemist and bacteriologist.

Gillies approach, flap, operation   a procedure in which the instrument is inserted deep to the deep lamina of temporalis fascia through a scalp incision and used to elevate depressed zygomatic complex fractures.

   Sir Harold Delf Gillies (1882–1960), British plastic surgeon.

Giraldes, organ of   a vestige of the Wolffian body on the posterior aspect of the testicle.

   Joaquim Albino Cardoso Casado Giraldes (1808–1875), Portuguese anatomist and surgeon.

Glanzmann’s thrombasthenia   a hereditary platelet abnormality characterized by defective clot retraction, prolonged bleeding time, and related symptoms such as epistaxis and inappropriate bleeding.

   Eduard Glanzmann (1887–1959), Swiss paediatrician.

Glenn shunt   a surgical operation for children born with cyanotic heart disease, in which the superior vena cava is anastomosed to the right pulmonary artery so that blood bypasses the malformed right chambers of the heart and is shunted directly into the lungs to be oxygenated.

   William WL Glenn (1914–2003), Chief of Cardiovascular Surgery, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, USA.

Glisson’s (Glissonian) capsule, sheath   the fibrous capsule of the liver.

   Francis Glisson (1597–1677), Regius Professor of Medicine, Cambridge, UK. Described rickets in 1671.

Goethe, ossicle of   the incus (an auditory ossicle).

   Johann Wolfgang Goethe (1749–1832), German poet, philosopher and scientist.

Goldenhaar’s syndrome   hemifacial microsomia. A syndrome of dermoid cysts, auricular appendices, asymmetrical malformations of the face, and vertebral abnormalities.

   Maurice Goldenhaar (1924–2001), American physician.

Golgi: cells, neurones   GABAergic cerebellar interneurones;

complexes, apparatus, bodies   membranous cellular organelles or vesicles;

corpuscles   tactile end organs in skin and muscle;

staining technique   a silver staining method for neurones;

tendon organ   a proprioceptive sensory nerve ending embedded among the fibres of a tendon.

   Camillo Golgi (1844–1926), Professor of Histology and Anatomy successively in Padua and then Siena, Italy; shared the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine (1906) with Ramon Santiago y Cajal for their work on the structure of the nervous system.

Goodpasture’s syndrome   an autoimmune condition in which autoantibodies damage basal laminae, primarily affecting renal and lung function.

   Ernest William Goodpasture (1886–1960), pathologist, Tennessee, USA.

Gorlin syndrome   nevoid basal-cell carcinoma syndrome (NBCC syndrome).

   Robert J Gorlin (1923–2006), American oral pathologist and human geneticist.

Graafian follicle   the mature ovarian follicle.

   Regnier de Graaf (1641–1673), Dutch anatomist and physician, Delft, Netherlands.

Grapow, vertical bands of   vertical connections between the palmar skin and palmar aponeurosis (Grapow M 1887 Die Anatomie und physiologische Anatomie der Palmaraponeurose. Arch Anat Physiol 2–3:143–58).

Gratiolet, ‘pli de passage’ of   Gratiolet introduced the term plis de passage for some interconnecting gyri in the cerebral cortex.

   Louis-Pierre Gratiolet (1815–1865), anatomist and zoologist, became Professor of Zoology, Paris, France.

Graves’ disease   a disorder of the thyroid, usually of autoimmune aetiology, characterized by at least two of the following: hyperthyroidism, goitre and exophthalmos.

   Robert James Graves (1796–1853), Irish physician.

Grayson’s ligament   fascial fibres that pass from the lateral sides of the phalanges volar to the neurovascular bundle (Grayson J 1941 The cutaneous ligaments of the digits. J Anat 75:164–75).

   J Grayson, Professor of Anatomy, Manchester, UK.

Grey Turner’s sign   bluish discoloration in the left loin caused by extravasated blood in acute pancreatitis – an uncommon physical sign.

   George Grey Turner (1877–1951), surgeon, Royal Victoria Infirmary, Newcastle upon Tyne, and Professor of Surgery, Royal Postgraduate Medical School, Hammersmith, London, UK.

Gruber, petrosphenoidal ligament of   a ligament that spans between the petrous apex and the posterior clinoid process, between the meningeal and periosteal layers of the dura mater; the insertion and thickness of the ligament may vary (see also Dorello’s canal).

   Wenzel Leopold Gruber (1814–1890), Russian anatomist.

Guérin’s fracture   a Le Fort I level fracture of the maxilla.

   Alphonse Guérin (1816–1895), surgeon, Paris, France.

Guillain–Barré syndrome   acute idiopathic polyneuritis.

   Georges Guillain (1876–1951), French neurologist; Jean Alexandre Barré (1880–1967), French neurologist.

Guillain-Mollaret triangle   dentato-rubro-olivary circuit.

   Georges Charles Guillain (1876–1961), French neurologist; Pierre Mollaret (1898–1987), French physician.

Guyon’s canal   the canal for the ulnar nerve and vessels; defined medially by the pisiform, and posteriorly by the flexor retinaculum.

   Jean Casimir Guyon (1831–1920), surgeon, Paris, France.

Haglund’s disease, syndrome, deformity   an abnormal prominence of the posterior superior lateral aspect of the os calcis.

   Sims Emil Patrik Haglund (1870–1937), Swedish orthopaedic surgeon.

Haller’s: arches   the medial and lateral arcuate ligaments (or lumbocostal arches);

cells   infraorbital ethmoidal cells (synonym: orbitoethmoidal cells), which may be specified as either anterior or posterior and which may lie lateral to the infundibulum and then open into the middle meatus. They grow into the bony orbital floor and may obstruct the ostia of either the ethmoidal infundibulum or the maxillary sinus during endonasal procedures;

circle of, zonula of   see Zinn, circle of, zonula of;

layer   a layer of large blood vessels in the choroid derived from the short posterior ciliary arteries.

   Victor Albrecht von Haller (1708–1777), Professor of Anatomy, Physiology, Surgery and Botany, University of Göttingen, Germany.

Hallermann–Streiff syndrome   oculomandibulofacial syndrome.

   Wilhelm Hallermann (1909–2005), German ophthalmologist; Enrico Bernardo Streiff (1908–1988), Italian-Swiss ophthalmologist.

Hallgren syndrome   see Usher syndrome (Hallgren B 1959 Retinitis pigmentosa combined with congenital deafness; with vestibulo-cerebellar ataxia and mental abnormality in a proportion of cases: a clinical and genetico-statistical study. Acta Psychiat Neurol Scand 138:5–101).

Harris’s growth lines   transverse juxta-epiphyseal lines of long bones seen on X-ray, which represent temporary growth arrest.

   Henry Harris (1886–1951), Professor of Anatomy, Cambridge, UK.

Hartmann’s pouch   dilation above the neck of the gallbladder – a pathological entity produced by a contained gallstone.

   Henri Hartmann (1860–1952), Professor of Surgery, Faculty of Medicine, Paris, France.

Hasner’s valve   otherwise known as the plica lacrimalis, a fold of mucous membrane that forms an imperfect cover at the lower opening of the nasolacrimal duct into the inferior nasal meatus.

   Joseph Hasner, Ritter von Artha (1819–1892), Austrian ophthalmologist.

Hassall’s corpuscles   spherical or ovoid bodies found in the medulla of the thymus, composed of concentric arrays of epithelial cells that contain keratohyalin and bundles of cytoplasmic filaments.

   Arthur Hill Hassall (1817–1894), English chemist and physician.

Haversian: canals   central vascular channels in Haversian systems;

systems   cylindrical units of tissue (osteons) in compact bone.

   Clopton Havers (1817–1894), physician practising first in London, then in the Isle of Wight, UK.

Hawkins sign   subchondral lucency of the talar dome, occurring secondary to subchondral atrophy 6–8weeks after a fracture of the talar neck (Hawkins LG 1970 Fractures of the neck of the talus. J Bone Joint Surg Am 52:991–1002).

Heidenhain’s trichrome stain   a stain for connective tissue.

   Rudolf Peter Heinrich Heidenhain (1834–1897), Polish physiologist, Breslau.

Heller’s myotomy, cardiomyotomy   a surgical procedure in which the muscles of the cardia (lower oesophageal sphincter) are cut, allowing food and liquids to pass to the stomach; the procedure may be open or closed (laparoscopic) (Heller E 1914 Extramuköse Kardioplastik beim chronischen Kardiospasmus mit Dilatation des Oesophagus. Mitt Grenzgeb Med Chir 27:141–9).

   Ernest Heller (1877–1964), German surgeon.

Henle’s: accessory paraflocculus of Henle   the dorsal leaf of the cerebellar flocculus;

conjunctival crypts of Henle   infoldings of the conjunctiva;

fibres   the ‘axons’ of foveal retinal cones running parallel to the retinal surface;

gastrocolic trunk of Henle   the confluence of the right superior colic and right superior gastroepiploic veins, draining into the superior mesenteric vein at the inferior border of the neck of the pancreas;

layer   the outer layer of cells in the root sheath of a hair;

loop of Henle   the looped portion of the renal tubule.

   Friedrich Gustav Henle (1808–1885), Professor of Anatomy in Zurich, Switzerland, then Heidelberg and Göttingen, Germany.

Henry: anterior approach of   an approach that provides exposure to the volar aspect of the radial shaft;

knot of   the crossing of the tendon of flexor hallucis longus deep to the tendon of flexor digitorum longus in the sole of the foot;

mobile wad of   three muscles, brachioradialis, extensor carpi radialis longus and extensor carpi radialis brevis, that are palpable below the lateral epicondyle of the humerus, lying on the lateral aspect of the radius.

   Arnold Kirkpatrick Henry (1886–1962), Professor of Anatomy, Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Ireland.

Hensen’s: cells, stripe   in the organ of Corti (see above) to the outer side of the cells of Deiters (see above);

node   thickening at the site of the first formation of the primitive streak.

   Viktor Hensen (1834–1924), Professor of Physiology, Kiel, Germany.

Hering–Breuer reflex   a lung stretch reflex mediated by the vagus.

   Carl Ewald Hering (1834–1918), physiologist, Academy of Military Medicine, Vienna, Austria, and then Leipzig, Germany; Josef Breuer (1842–1925), psychiatrist and physiologist, Vienna, Austria, where he collaborated with Hering.

Hering, canals of   fine terminal ductules lined by cuboidal epithelium, linking the intralobular bile canaliculi with bile ducts in the portal canals.

   Carl Ewald Hering (see above).

Heschl: sulcus of   the anterior border of the planum temporale;

Heschl’s transverse temporal gyri   gyri on the temporal lobe of the brain.

   Richard Heschl (1824–1881), Professor of Pathology, Cracow, Poland, then Professor of Clinical Medicine, Graz, Austria.

Hesselbach’s: fascia   the cribriform fascia;

ligament   the interfoveolar ligament;

triangle   the inguinal triangle.

   Franz Kaspar Hesselbach (1759–1816), German surgeon and anatomist.

Heubner’s artery   the artery that supplies the anteromedial part of the head of the caudate nucleus and the anteroinferior internal capsule.

   Johann Otto Leonhard Heubner (1843–1926), German paediatrician.

Heuser’s membrane   the parietal hypoblast layer.

   Chester Heuser (1885–1965), American embryologist.

Hill–Sachs lesion   cortical depression of the posterolateral head of the humerus related to impaction of the humeral head with the inferior glenoid fossa in anterior shoulder dislocation.

   Harold Arthur Hill (1901–1973), American radiologist; Maurice David Sachs (1909–1987), American radiologist.

Hilton’s law   nerves crossing a joint supply the joint, the muscles acting on the joint and the skin overlying the joint.

   John Hilton (1805–1878), surgeon, Guy’s Hospital, London, UK.

Hirschsprung’s disease   megacolon resulting from congenital absence of autonomic ganglion cells in the distal contracted segment.

   Harald Hirschsprung (1830–1916), physician, Queen Louise Children’s Hospital, Copenhagen, Denmark.

His: angle of   the normally acute angle between the abdominal oesophagus and the fundus of the stomach at the oesophagogastric junction;

bundle of   the atrioventricular bundle of the heart;

furcula of   an inverted U that appears in the central wall of the developing pharynx;

sinus of   the caudal portion of the second branchial arch, as well as the third and fourth arches, which becomes submerged in the cervical sinus of His, a shallow ectodermal pit.

   Wilhelm His (Junior) (1863–1934), Professor of Anatomy successively at Leipzig, Germany; Basle, Switzerland; and Göttingen and Berlin, Germany. Son of Wilhelm His (Senior).

Hitselberger’s sign   loss of sensation in the posterosuperior part of the external acoustic meatus (external auditory canal) that may be an early sign of an acoustic tumour.

   William E Hitselberger (1930–2014), American neurosurgeon, a pioneer in developing the auditory brainstem implant.

Hjortsjö’s crook   in the biliary tract, the right posterior sectional duct normally hooks over the origin of the right anterior sectional portal vein, forming ‘Hjortsjö’s crook’ (Hjortsjö CH 1951 The topography of the intrahepatic duct system. Acta Anat (Basel) 11:599–615).

Hoboken, valves of   constrictions of the contours of the umbilical arteries along their course through the umbilical cord.

   Nicolas van Hoboken (1632–1678), Professor of Anatomy, Harderwyk, then Professor of Medicine and Mathematics, Steinfurt, Netherlands.

Hodgkin’s lymphoma   a haematopoietic neoplasm characterized by cancerous Hodgkin and Reed–Sternberg cells (HRS cells) in an inflammatory background. The aetiology of the disease is not well understood.

   Thomas Hodgkin (1798–1866), English physician and pathologist.

Hofbauer cells   placental macrophages in the chorionic villi.

   J Isfred Hofbauer (1878–1961), American gynaecologist.

Holden, line of   the transverse skin crease at the groin caused by flexion of the hip.

   Luther Holden (1815–1905), surgeon, St Bartholomew’s Hospital, London, UK.

Holmes tremor   a tremor that is usually slow and large in amplitude, and may be present at rest, with movement, and often with sustained posture.

   Gordon Morgan Holmes (1876–1965), British neurologist.

Holmes–Adie syndrome   a disorder characterized by one eye with a pupil that is larger than normal and constricts slowly in bright light (tonic pupil), and absence of deep tendon reflexes, usually in the Achilles tendon.

   Gordon Morgan Holmes (1876–1965), Irish neurologist; William John Adie (1886–1935), British physician and neurologist.

Hopkinson squeeze test   a test to assess the inferior tibiofibular joint, by compressing the fibula to the tibia at the midpoint of the leg: an injured syndesmosis will result in pain felt in the area of the inferior tibiofibular joint (Hopkinson WJ, St Pierre P, Ryan JB et al 1990 Syndesmosis sprains of the ankle. Foot Ankle 10:325–30).

Horner’s syndrome, Bernard–Horner syndrome   ptosis and pupillary constriction following interruption of the sympathetic supply to the eyelid and pupil, respectively (hemifacial anhidrosis may also occur).

   Johann Horner (1831–1886), Professor of Ophthalmology, Zurich, Switzerland; Claude Bernard (1813–1878), French physiologist, considered one of the founders of experimental medicine.

Hotchkiss approach   anteromedial ‘over the top’ surgical approach to the elbow performed between flexor carpi ulnaris and flexor carpi radialis (or palmaris longus, when present); it provides good access to the tip of the coronoid process and the whole anterior elbow joint (Hotchkiss R 1998 Surgical technique. In: Hotchkiss R (ed) Compass Universal Hinge. Surgical Technique. Memphis: Smith & Nephew, 8–12).

   Robert N Hotchkiss, American orthopaedic surgeon.

Houston, valves of   three intraluminal folds in the wall of the rectum.

   John Houston (1802–1845), Irish surgeon and anatomist.

Howship’s lacunae   absorption spaces in bone.

   John Howship (1781–1841), surgeon, St George’s and Charing Cross Hospitals, London, UK. Suffered from osteomyelitis of the tibia and made a special study of bone pathology.

   Howship–Romberg sign:

   see Romberg sign.

Humphrey, ligament of   meniscofemoral ligament – Humphrey described this ligament as running from the lateral meniscus to the posterior cruciate ligament.

   George Murray Humphrey (1820–1896), Professor of Anatomy and then of Surgery, Cambridge, UK. Founder of Journal of Anatomy.

Hunter’s canal   the subsartorial canal.

   John Hunter (1728–1793), surgeon, St George’s Hospital, London, UK. Described ligation of the femoral artery in the subsartorial canal for popliteal aneurysm. John Hunter is often described as the Founder of Scientific Surgery.

Huntington’s disease, chorea   an autosomal dominant disease characterized by chronic progressive chorea and mental deterioration.

   George Sumner Huntington (1850–1916), American physician.

Hurler’s syndrome   a genetic disorder resulting in a deficiency in breakdown of mucopolysaccharides in the extracellular matrix.

   Gertrud Hurler (1889–1965), German paediatrician.

Huschke: foramen of   otherwise known as the foramen tympanicum. An uncommon developmental defect in the anteroinferior aspect of the bony external acoustic meatus. which usually closes by the fifth year but may persist throughout life;

inferior longitudinal sulcus of   (synonym: collateral sulcus) a structure that separates the fusiform gyrus from the parahippocampal gyrus of the limbic lobe.

   Emil Huschke (1797–1858), German anatomist and embryologist.

Hutchinson’s incisors   pegged lateral incisors and notched central incisors, seen in congenital syphilis.

   Sir Jonathan Hutchinson (1828–1913), British surgeon, pathologist, pioneer in the study of congenital syphilis.

Huxley’s layer   the inner layer of cells of the root sheath of a hair.

   Thomas Henry Huxley (1825–1895), lecturer in Natural History, Royal School of Mines, UK. An early supporter of Darwinism.

Hyrtl’s anastomosis   an occasional anastomosis between umbilical arteries in the placenta.

   Joseph Hyrtl (1811–1894), Austrian anatomist.

Jackson’s membrane   a peritoneal fold between the caecum or ascending colon and the lateral abdominal wall.

   Jabez North Jackson (1868–1935), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Kansas City, USA.

Jacobson’s organ   otherwise known as the vomeronasal organ. A bilateral structure in the anteroinferior wall of the nasal septum just dorsal to the paraseptal cartilages, presumed to be analogous to the vomeronasal organ of other vertebrates: function in humans not yet established, but might be involved in the detection of pheromones.

   Ludwig Lewin Jacobson (1783–1843), Danish surgeon.

Jacoby, border tissue of   a posterior extension of astrocytes from the intermediary tissue of Kuhnt, located internal to the border tissue of Elschnig at the optic nerve head (Jacoby E 1905 Über die Neuroglia des Sehnerven. Klin Mbl Augenheilk 43:129–37).

Jadassohn–Lewandowsky syndrome   an autosomal dominant skin disorder characterized predominantly by thickened nails, palmoplantar hyperkeratosis, keratosis pilaris, hyperkeratotic follicular papules on the sites of friction, hair abnormalities and hyperhidrosis of the palms and soles (Jadassohn J, Lewandowsky F 1906 Jacob’s Ikonographia Dermatologica. Berlin: Urban & Schwarzenberg).

Jensen, intermediate sulcus of   a downward-projecting side branch of the intraparietal sulcus that descends across the inferior parietal lobule. It starts at the dorsal hemispheric margin and divides the area between the posterior ascending ramus of the Sylvian gyrus and the angular gyrus as it courses ventrally (Jensen J 1870 Die Furchen und Windungen der menschlichen Grosshirn-Hemisphären. Berlin: Georg Reimer).

Jeune syndrome   asphyxiating thoracic dystrophy (Jeune M, Carron R, Beraud C et al 1954 Polychondrodystrophie avec blocage thoracique d’évolution fatale. Pediatrie, Lyon 9:390–2).

   Mathis Jeune (1910–1983), French paediatrician.

Joll’s triangle   otherwise known as the sternothyrolaryngeal triangle and used to identify the external laryngeal branch of the superior laryngeal nerve during thyroid surgery, the triangle is formed laterally by the upper pole of the thyroid gland and the superior thyroid vessels, superiorly by the attachment of the strap muscles to the thyroid cartilage and medially by the midline.

   Cecil Augustus Joll (1885–1945), English surgeon.

Joubert’s syndrome   a ciliopathy, one of a group of rare genetic disorders characterized by decreased muscle tone, difficulties with coordination, abnormal eye movements, abnormal breathing pattern and cognitive impairment (Joubert M, Eisenring JJ, Robb JP et al 1969 Familial agenesis of the cerebellar vermis. A syndrome of episodic hyperpnea, abnormal eye movements, ataxia, and retardation. Neurology 19:813–25).

   Marie Joubert, paediatric neurologist.

Kager’s fat pad   (synonym: pre-Achilles fat pad) a structure located in Kager’s triangle between the Achilles tendon, the superior cortex of the calcaneus and flexor hallucis longus (both muscle and tendon) (Kager H 1939 Zur Klinik und Diagnostik des Achillessehnenrisses. Der Chirurg 11:691–5).

Kartagener’s syndrome   a genetic disorder (immotile cilia syndrome) affecting axonemal dynein function.

   Manes Kartagener (1897–1975), Swiss physician.

Kawase’s triangle of the middle fossa   an area that lies between the lateral margin of the greater petrosal nerve (medial border), the lateral edge of the trigeminal nerve behind the point where the greater petrosal nerve passes below its lateral surface to the crest of the petrous apex (lateral border), and a line along the connection of the posterior border of the mandibular division of the trigeminal nerve and the trigeminal ganglion (the crest of petrous apex) to the centre of the geniculate ganglion (Kawase T, van Loeren HR, Keller JT et al 1996 Meningeal architecture of the cavernous sinus: clinical and surgical implications. Neurosurg 39:527–36).

Keen approach   Keen categorized zygomatic fractures as those of the arch, the body or the sutural disjunction. He was the first to introduce an intraoral approach to the zygomatic arch, in which an incision is made in the gingivobuccal sulcus (Keen WW 1909 Surgery: Its Principles and Practice. Philadelphia: WB Saunders).

Kehr’s sign   the occurrence of acute pain in the tip of the shoulder due to the presence of blood or other irritants in the peritoneal cavity when an individual is lying down and the legs are elevated. Kehr’s sign in the left shoulder is considered a classic symptom of a ruptured spleen.

   Johannes Otto Kehr (1862–1916), German surgeon.

Kerckring: valves of   the plicae circulares;

Kerckring’s centre   an occasional independent centre of ossification in the occipital bone.

   Theodor Kerckring (1640–1693), Dutch anatomist.

Kienböck’s disease   slowly progressing degeneration of the lunate bone of the wrist.

   Robert Kienböck (1871–1953), Austrian radiologist.

Kiesselbach’s plexus   a site of haemorrhage on the nasal septum.

   Wilhelm Kiesselbach (1839–1902), ear, nose and throat surgeon, Erlangen, Germany.

Killian’s: dehiscence   a gap between the attachments of the inferior constrictor of the pharynx to the cricoid and thyroid cartilages. Site of origin of a pharyngeal pouch;

sling   the cricopharyngeal sphincter;

triangle   a triangular area in the wall of the pharynx between the oblique fibres of the inferior constrictor muscle and the transverse fibres of cricopharyngeus, through which a Zenker’s diverticulum may occur.

   Gustav Killian (1860–1921), Professor of Laryngorhinology, successively in Freiburg and Berlin, Germany.

Kindler’s syndrome   congenital poikiloderma with bullae and progressive cutaneous atrophy.

   Theresa Kindler (1890–1975), Austrian-born dermatologist.

Kirk’s arcade   an anastomosis between branches of the dorsal pancreatic artery and the right gastro-epiploic artery (Kirk E 1931 Untersuchungen über die gröbere und feinere topographische Verteilung der Arterien, Venen und Ausführungsgänge in der menschlichen Bauchspeicheldrüse. Z Ges Anat 94:822–75).

Klingler’s method/technique   a method of brain fixation and dissection based on freezing and thawing the brain and subsequently peeling away tissues to expose white matter tracts (Agrawal A, Kapfhammer JP, Kress A et al 2011 Josef Klingler’s models of white matter tracts: influences on neuroanatomy, neurosurgery, and neuroimaging. Neurosurgery 69:238–52).

   Josef Klingler (1888–1963), Swiss neuroanatomical ‘technician’.

Klippel–Feil syndrome   congenital fusion or reduction in number of the cervical vertebrae.

   Maurice Klippel (1858–1942), neurologist, Salpêtrière, Paris, France; André Feil (1884–1955), French neurologist.

Klippel–Trenaunay syndrome   a rare congenital condition where blood vessels and/or lymph vessels fail to form properly.

   Maurice Klippel (1858–1942), French physician; Paul Trénaunay (1875–?), French neurologist.

Klumpke’s paralysis   injury to lowest root of brachial plexus (T1).

   Augusta Déjerine-Klumpke (1859–1927), neurologist, Paris, France. Married to another neurologist, Joseph Déjerine.

Koch, triangle of   a triangular area in the wall of the right atrium that marks the site of the atrioventricular node.

   Walter Karl Koch (1880–1962), physician and pathologist, Berlin and Freiburg, Germany.

Kocher’s manoeuvre, method   an invagination method for radical operation for an inguinal hernia.

   Theodor Kocher (1841–1917), made numerous contributions to surgery. Awarded Nobel Prize in Medicine or Physiology (1909) for his pioneering work on physiology, pathology and surgery of the thyroid gland.

Köhler’s disease   avascular necrosis of the tarsal navicular bone and, less frequently, the patella, possibly due to repetitive compressive forces that cause a loss of blood supply and fragmentation in a bone that is not fully ossified. More common in males; onset at 3–8years of age. Asymptomatic or painful on the medial side of the foot; tenderness on palpation and swelling over area of navicular bone; slight, usually unilateral, limp.

   Alban Köhler (1874–1947), German radiologist.

Kohn, interalveolar pores of   pores that link adjacent alveolar air spaces of the lung.

   Hans Kohn (1866–1935), pathologist, Berlin, Germany.

Kölliker–Fuse nucleus   the substantia intermedia centralis in the spinal cord.

   Rudolf Albert von Kölliker (1817–1905), Swiss anatomist.

Kommerell, diverticulum of   an aortic diverticulum associated with an aberrant right subclavian artery.

   Burckhard Friedrich Kommerell (1901–1990), German radiologist.

Kooy, dorsal cap of   a subnucleus of the inferior olive: processes optokinetic information and projects to the contralateral flocculus and nodulus (Kooy FH 1916 The inferior olive in vertebrates. Thesis, Haarlem: Erven Bohn; Kooy FH 1917 The inferior olive in vertebrates. Folia Neurabiol 10:205–369).

Körner’s septum   a dense bony plate in the mastoid process that represents the persistence of the petrosquamous suture line. The septum divides the mastoid process into a superficial squamous portion and a deep petrous portion (Korner O 1926 Das Septum petrosquamosum (mastoideum) und seine klinische Bedeutung. Arch Ohren Nasen Kehlkopfheilk 17:137).

Korsakoff psychosis, syndrome   a syndrome of anterograde and retrograde amnesia with confabulation, associated with alcoholic or non-alcoholic polyneuritis, described as ‘cerebropathia psychica toxaemia’ by Korsakoff; currently used synonymously with ‘amnestic syndrome’.

   Sergei Sergeievich Korsakoff (1854–1900), Russian neuropsychiatrist.

Kraissl’s lines   the lines of greatest tension in the skin.

   Cornelius Kraissl (1902–1999), plastic surgeon, New Jersey, USA.

Krause, glands of   accessory lacrimal glands in the subconjunctival tissue of the upper fornix.

   Karl Friedrich Theodor Krause (1797–1868), Professor of Anatomy, Hanover, Germany.

Krebs’ cycle   the citric acid cycle – the oxidative energy production pathway in mitochondria.

   Sir Hans Adolf Krebs (1900–1981), German-born British biochemist.

Kugel’s anastomotic artery   the arteria anastomotica auricularis magna (synonym: atrial anastomotic branch of circumflex branch of left coronary artery) (Kugel MA 1927 Anatomical studies on the coronary arteries and their branches. I. Arteria anastomotica auricularis magna. Am Heart J 3:260–70).

Kuhn classification   a classification of frontal ethmoidal cells into types 1 to 4 (Kuhn FA 1996 Chronic frontal sinusitis: the endoscopic frontal recess approach. Oper Techn Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 7:222–9).

Kuhnt: central tissue meniscus of   a thickening of the astroglial membrane (of Elschnig) covering the optic nerve head at the centre of the disc;

intermediary layer of, intermediary tissue of   a collar of astrocytes that separates the optic nerve head from the retina.

   Hermann Kuhnt (1850–1925), German ophthalmologist.

Kulchitsky cells   neuroendocrine cells in the lung and gut.

   Nicholas Kulchitsky (1856–1925), Professor of Histology, Kharkov, Russia. After the Russian Revolution, went to London, UK, to continue his work in neuropathology at University College.

Kuntz, nerve of   an inconstant intrathoracic ramus that joins the second intercostal nerve to the ventral ramus of the first thoracic nerve, proximal to the point where the latter gives a branch to the brachial plexus.

   Albert Kuntz (1879–1957), American anatomist.

Kupffer cells   resident liver macrophages.

   Karl Wilhelm von Kupffer (1829–1902), Professor of Anatomy successively at Kiel, Königsberg and Munich, Germany.

Labbé, inferior anastomotic vein of   a vein that connects the superficial middle cerebral vein to the transverse sinus.

   Léon Labbé (1832–1916), French surgeon.

Ladd’s bands   congenital bands across the duodenum in volvulus neonatorum.

   William Edward Ladd (1880–1967), surgeon, Boston Children’s Hospital, USA.

Laimer’s: diverticulum   a pulsion diverticulum located below cricopharyngeus;

triangle   see Killian’s triangle.

   Eduard Laimer (1857–1934), anatomist, Graz, Austria.

Lancisi, muscle of   the main medial papillary muscle of the right ventricle (quoted in: Tandler J 1913 Anatomie des Herzens. In: Bardeleben’s Handbuch der Anatomie des Menschen. Jena: Gustav Fischer).

   Giovanni Maria Lancisi (1654–1720), Italian physician, epidemiologist and anatomist.

Landsmeer’s ligaments   the transverse and oblique retinacular ligaments of the fingers.

   Johan Landsmeer (1919–1999), Professor of Anatomy, Leiden, Netherlands.

Langer’s lines   cleavage or crease lines in the skin produced by the arrangement of the subcutaneous fibrous tissues.

   Karl Ritter von Edenberg Langer (1819–1887), Professor of Anatomy, Hungary, and then Vienna, Austria.

Langerhans: cells   dendritic cell of haemopoietic origin, in the epidermis and other epithelia;

islets of   clumps of insulin- and other hormone-secreting cells of the pancreas.

   Paul Langerhans (1847–1888), Professor of Pathology, Freiburg, Germany. Described the islet cells in his doctoral thesis in 1869, at the age of 22.

Langhans cells   cells of the villous cytotrophoblast.

   Theodor Langhans (1839–1915), pathologist, Berne, Switzerland.

Laplace’s equation   the prototypical elliptic partial differential equation.

   Pierre-Simon Laplace (1749–1827), French mathematician and astronomer.

Ledderhose’s disease   plantar fascial fibromatosis.

   Georg Ledderhose (1855–1925), German surgeon. Discovered glucosamine while working on cartilage with Ernst Felix Immanuel Hoppe-Seyler (1825–1895) in Strasbourg, France.

Le Fort I, II and III fractures   a system of classification of facial fractures.

   René Le Fort (1869–1951), surgeon, Lille, France.

Legueu and Juvara, vertical septa of   vertical septa that pass from the transverse fibres of the palmar aponeurosis to the underlying deep transverse metacarpal ligament, forming fibro-osseous compartments (Legueu F, Juvara E 1892 Des aponévroses de la paume de la main. Bull Soc Anat Paris 6:383–400).

Leydig cells   the interstitial testosterone-secreting cells of the testis.

   Franz von Leydig (1821–1908), Professor of Histology successively at Würzburg, Tübingen and Bonn, Germany.

Lieberkühn, crypts of   tubular glands of the small intestine.

   Johann Nathaniel Lieberkühn (1711–1756), physician and anatomist, Berlin, Germany. These glands were described in 1688 by Marcello Malpighi (1628–1694), Italian physician and biologist, often cited as ‘the father of microscopical anatomy and histology’.

Li Fraumeni syndrome   a rare autosomal dominant cancer predisposition syndrome first reported in 1969 by Frederick Li and Joseph Fraumeni from the National Cancer Institute, Rockville, Maryland, USA (Li FP, Fraumeni JF Jr, Mulvihill JJ et al 1988 A cancer family syndrome in twenty-four kindreds. Cancer Res 48:5358–62).

Liliequist’s membrane   an arachnoid membrane passing from the dorsum sellae to the anterior edge of the mammillary body. Described by Key and Retzius in 1875 and ‘rediscovered’ in 1956 in Liliequist’s cadaveric pneumoencephalographic studies. (Liliequist B 1956 The anatomy of the subarachnoid cisterns. Acta Radiol 46:61–71).

Lisfranc: joint   the tarsometatarsal joint;

Lisfranc’s ligament   an interosseous ligament between the second metatarsal and first cuneiform bone of the foot.

   Jacques de St Martin Lisfranc (1790–1847), Professor of Surgery, Paris, France.

Lissauer, fasciculus of, tract of   the ascending tract in the spinal cord.

   Heinrich Lissauer (1861–1891), neurologist, Breslau, Poland.

Lister’s tubercle   a prominence on the posterior surface of the distal radius, ulnar to the groove for the tendon of extensor pollicis longus.

   Lord Joseph Lister (1827–1912), successively Professor of Surgery at Glasgow, Edinburgh and King’s College, London, UK.

Little’s area   a site of haemorrhage on the nasal septum.

   James Laurence Little (1836–1885), Professor of Surgery, University of Vermont, USA.

Littre, glands of   small mucous glands of the male urethra.

   Alexis Littre (1658–1726), French anatomist and surgeon.

Lockwood, suspensory ligament of   the thickened area of contact between Tenon’s capsule and the sheaths of inferior rectus and inferior oblique in the orbit.

   Charles Barrett Lockwood (1856–1914), British surgeon and anatomist, St Bartholomew’s Hospital, London, UK.

Louis, angle of   the sternal angle – the angle formed on the anterior surface of the sternum at the junction of its body and manubrium.

   Antoine Louis (1723–1792), Maître de Chirurgie and later Professor of Physiology, Royal College of Surgeons, Paris, France. He designed the prototype of the guillotine, which was originally nicknamed the ‘Louison’ or ‘Louisette’.

Lower, intervenous tubercle of   a structure that lies between the fossa ovalis and the superior vena cava. Richard Lower (1631–1691), English physician. (Lower R 1669 Tractatus de corde. Item de motu, colore sanguinis et chyli in eum transitum. London: J Redmayne & J Allestry, ).

Ludwig’s angina   a potentially life-threatening, rapidly expanding, diffuse inflammation of the submandibular and sublingual spaces, occurring most often in young adults with dental infections.

   Wilhelm Friedrich von Ludwig (1790–1865), German surgeon and obstetrician.

Lugaro cell   an inhibitory interneurone in the cerebellum.

   Ernesto Lugaro (1870–1940), Italian neuropsychiatrist.

Luschka: bursa of (lateral Luschka aperture)   an accessory pharyngeal recess in front of the anterior arch of the atlas;

duct of   small, gland-like tubular structures in the wall of the gallbladder adjacent to the liver, especially in the part covered with peritoneum;

foramen of   the lateral aperture in the roof of the fourth cerebral ventricle;

uncovertebral joints of   small synovial joints on either side of the intervertebral cartilaginous joint in cervical vertebrae C3–C7 (between the uncinate process of the inferior vertebral body and the bevelled lateral border of the superior body at each level).

   Hubert Luschka (1820–1875), Professor of Anatomy, Tübingen, Germany.

McBurney’s point   the reputed site of maximal tenderness in appendicitis.

   Charles McBurney (1845–1913), American surgeon.

Macewen’s triangle   the surface marking of the mastoid antrum.

   Sir William Macewen (1848–1924), Scottish surgeon. Established the treatment of intracranial complications of middle ear suppuration.

McGregor’s patch   an area of fibrous attachment between the anterior edge of the parotid fascia and the dermis of the skin of the cheek (Rossell-Perry P 2013 The zygomatic ligament of the face: a critical review. OA Anat 1:3).

   McLaughlin lesion:

   reverse Hill–Sachs lesion – an impaction fracture of the anteromedial aspect of the humeral head following posterior dislocation of the humerus.

   Harrison Lloyd McLaughlin (1906–1970), American orthopaedic surgeon.

Mackenrodt, ligament of   the transverse cervical (or cardinal) ligament of the uterus.

   Alwin Mackenrodt (1859–1925), Professor of Gynaecology, Berlin, Germany.

McKenzie branch of first cervical nerve   a communicating branch between the (spinal) accessory nerve and the anterior root of the first cervical nerve (McKenzie KG 1955 The surgical treatment of spasmodic torticollis. Clin Neurosurg 2:37–43).

Magendie, foramen of, aperture of   the median aperture in the roof of the fourth ventricle.

   François Magendie (1783–1855), physician to the Hôtel Dieu, Paris, France.

Malassez, rests of   epithelial remnants of the enamel organ found in the periodontal ligament.

   Louis Charles Malassez (1842–1909), French surgeon and physiologist.

Mallory’s triple stain   Mallory’s acid fuchsin, orange G and aniline blue stain for connective tissue.

   Frank Burr Mallory (1862–1941), pathologist, Boston, USA.

   Marfan: aortic dissection –

   see below;

syndrome   an autosomal genetic disorder of the connective tissue characterized by a long body and extended limbs and fingers, often associated with cardiovascular abnormalities such as dissecting aortic aneurysms and valve defects, as well as subluxated ocular lenses.

   Antoine Bernard-Jean Marfan (1858–1942), Professor of Infantile Hygiene, Paediatric Clinic, University of Paris, France.

Marshall, vein of   the left atrial oblique vein, an embryonic remnant of the left superior caval vein which is enclosed within the Marshall ligament (Marshall J 1850 On the development of the great anterior veins in man and mammalia: including an account of certain remnants of fetal structure found in the adult, a comparative view of these great veins in the different mammalia, and an analysis of their occasional peculiarities in the human subject. Philos Trans R Soc Lond 140:133–69).

   John Marshall (1818–1891), English surgeon and anatomist.

Martin–Gruber anastomosis   an anomalous connection between the median and ulnar nerves in the forearm (Martin R 1763 Om nervernas allmänna egenskaper i menniskans kropp jemte nervernas särskilda anatomiska beskrifning. Stockholm: Lars Silvius. Gruber W 1870 Über die Verbindung des Nervus medianus mit dem Nervus ulnaris am Unterarme des Menschen und der Säugethiere. Archiv für pathologische Anatomie und Physiologie und für klinische Medizin 37:501–22); see Gruber above.

Martinotti cell, neurone   a fusiform neurone in the deepest layer of the cerebral cortex.

   Giovanni Martinotti (1857–1928), pathologist, Bologna, Italy.

Martius fat pad flap   a procedure used for complex fistula repair and as an interposition graft with vaginal reconstructive surgery (Martius H 1928 Die operative Wiederherstellung der vollkommen fehlenden Harnrohre und des Schlessmuskels derselben. Zentralbi Gynakol 52:480–6).

Masson’s trichrome stain   a stain for connective tissue.

   Claude Laurent Pierre Masson (1880–1959), French-born Canadian pathologist.

Mattox manoeuvre   a left medial visceral rotation – a surgical step to explore and handle Zone 1 and 2 retroperitoneal injuries (aorta, left iliac and pelvic vessels).

   Kenneth L Mattox (1938– ) American surgeon.

Maubrac, ansa of   an obsolete term for an anastomosis between the lateral deep branches of the cervical plexus and the accessory nerve (Maubrac G 1883 Recherches anatomiques et physiologiques sur le nerf SCM. Thesis, Bordeaux University (no. 38)).

Mayer–Rokitansky–Küster–Hauser syndrome   a syndrome characterized by congenital absence of the vagina, primary amenorrhoea, rudimentary cornua uteri and morphologically normal ovaries and Fallopian tubes situated on the side wall of the pelvis.

   August Franz Joseph Karl Mayer (1787–1865), German anatomist and physiologist; Karl Freiherr von Rokitansky (1804–1878), Austrian pathologist; Hermann Küster (1879–1964), German gynaecologist; Georges André Hauser (1921–2009), Swiss gynaecologist.

Mayo, prepyloric vein of   a tributary of the right gastric vein that passes anterior to the pylorus at the gastroduodenal junction, also called vena prepylorica [TA], and Latarget’s vein.

   William James Mayo (1861–1939), American physician and surgeon, one of the founders of the Mayo Clinic.

Meckel’s: cartilage   the cartilage of the first branchial arch;

cave   a cerebrospinal fluid-containing arachnoidal pouch protruding from the posterior cranial fossa. Located near the apex of the petrous part of the temporal bone, it houses the trigeminal ganglion and extends forwards, rather like an open-ended, three-fingered glove, enveloping the rootlets of the trigeminal nerve, the trigeminal ganglion and the ophthalmic, maxillary and mandibular divisions of the trigeminal nerve;

diverticulum   the remains of the vitellointestinal duct.

   Johann Meckel (1781–1833), Professor of Anatomy, Halle, Germany. His grandfather was Professor of Anatomy in Berlin and described the pterygopalatine ganglion and the dural sac, which contains the ganglion of the trigeminal nerve. His father was also Professor of Anatomy in Halle.

Meibomian glands   the tarsal glands of the eyelid. If blocked, they become distended into Meibomian cysts.

   Heinrich Meibom (1638–1700), Professor of Medicine, History and Poetry, Helmstadt, Germany.

Meissner’s: corpuscles   tactile nerve endings in skin;

plexus   the submucosal autonomic plexus of the intestine.

   George Meissner (1829–1905), Professor of Anatomy and Physiology, Basle, Switzerland; Zoology and Physiology, Freiburg, Germany; and Physiology, Göttingen, Germany.

Mendel’s laws   the laws of inheritance of single-gene traits that form the basis of the science of genetics, first described by Gregor Mendel in 1865.

   Gregor Johann Mendel (1822–1884), abbot and pioneer of genetics from Brno, Czech Republic.

Ménière’s disease   aural or auditory vertigo.

   Prosper Ménière (1799–1862), French otorhinolaryngologist.

Mercier’s bar   a curved fold of mucous membrane extending across the bladder between the two ureteric orifices, produced by a transverse bundle of muscle fibres.

   Louis Auguste Mercier (1811–1882), French urologist.

Merkel: cells, corpuscles   sensory cells in the skin;

disc   a slowly adapting type I receptor, which lies in the basal epidermis of glabrous skin and is sensitive to sustained pressure.

   Friedrich Sigmund Merkel (1845–1919), Professor of Anatomy successively at Rostock, then Göttingen, Germany.

Meyer’s loop   the fibres of the geniculocalcarine tract that loop forwards in the temporal lobe.

   Adolf Meyer (1866–1950), American psychiatrist.

Meynert, basal nucleus of   part of the ‘substantia innominata’ of the basal forebrain; contains large cholinergic neurones that project to the cerebral cortex, amygdala and thalamus.

   Theodore Herman Meynert (1833–1892), Professor of Neurology, Vienna, Austria.

Mikulicz angle   the angle formed between the head and neck of the femur and its shaft.

   Johann (Jan) Freiherr von Mikulicz-Radecki (1850–1905), Polish surgeon in Germany.

Minor’s syndrome   dehiscence of the roof of the superior semicircular canal (Minor LB 2000 Superior canal dehiscence syndrome. Am J Otol 21:9–19).

Mirizzi syndrome   partial obstruction to the flow of bile and the appearance of mild jaundice as a result of biliary stones.

   Pablo Mirizzi (1893–1964), Argentinian physician.

Moll, glands of   modified sweat glands associated with the eyelashes.

   Jacob Antonius Moll (1832–1914), ophthalmologist, The Hague, Netherlands.

Monro, foramen of   the foramen between the lateral and third ventricles of the brain.

   Alexander Monro (1733–1817), Professor of Anatomy, Edinburgh, UK. The chair was also held by his father and his son – both also named Alexander.

Monteggia injury   a fracture of the upper portion of the ulna combined with dislocation of the radial head.

   Giovanni Battista Monteggia (1762–1815), Italian physician and surgeon.

Montgomery, glands of, tubercles of   sebaceous glands situated in the areola of the breast (previously described by Morgagni; see below).

   William Montgomery (1797–1859), Professor of Midwifery, Dublin, Ireland.

Morgagni: columns of   the columns of the anal canal;

concha   otherwise known as concha nasalis suprema, superior nasal choncha;

hernia   a congenital diaphragmatic hernia between the sternal and costal attachments of the diaphragm;

hydatid of   (synonyms: appendix testis, appendices vesiculosae epoophori) a cyst-like remnant of the Müllerian duct attached to a testis;

sinus   a sinus that lies between the superior pharyngeal constrictor and the base of the skull. Internally it is covered by mucosa and posteriorly by the pharyngobasilar fascia and is a route for the spread of neoplasms and infection from the nasopharynx to the base of the skull;

triangle(s) of   the right and left sternocostal triangles of Morgagni are openings in the anterior part of the respiratory diaphragmatic muscle, between the sternal and costal parts;

   Morgagni’s tubercle – otherwise known as the tuberculum septi nasi or the septal tubercle, it is a focal bulge of the anterior nasal septum at the level of the middle turbinate.

   Giovanni Battista Morgagni (1682–1771), Professor of Anatomy, Padua, Italy, for 59 years. Described as the founder of modern morbid anatomy.

Morgenstern, ‘criminal’ fold of   a constant peritoneal fold attached to the lower pole of the spleen near to the splenic flexure but distinct from the splenocolic ligament. It is most commonly responsible for iatrogenic injuries to the lower pole of the spleen during operation on the left upper quadrant.

   Leon Morgenstern (1919–2012), American surgeon.

Morison, hepatorenal pouch of   the right subhepatic space.

   James Rutherford Morison (1853–1939), Professor of Surgery, Durham, UK.

Moro reflex   the startle reflex.

   Ernst Moro (1874–1951), German physician.

Morquio syndrome   mucopolysaccharidosis type IV (MPS IV), an autosomal recessive disorder in which there is an inability to process keratan sulphate.

   Luis Morquio (1867–1935), Uruguayan physician.

Morton’s neuroma   a disease of the foot characterized by a sudden cramp-like pain in the metatarsal area radiating to the fourth and fifth toes, and sometimes to the calf of the leg. Compression of the plantar nerve by a tumour, arthritic changes or bursitis is the common cause.

   Thomas George Morton (1835–1903), American surgeon.

Müller: cells   neuroglial cells in the retina;

orbital muscle of   a collection of smooth muscle fibres spanning the infraorbital fissure. Its functions are uncertain;

superior tarsal muscle of   a thin lamina of smooth muscle that passes from the underside of levator palpebrae superioris to the upper margin of the superior tarsus.

   Heinrich Müller (1820–1864), Professor of Anatomy, Würzburg, Germany.

Müllerian duct (also Müllerian duct syndrome)   paramesonephric ducts. Persistent Müllerian duct syndrome is a disorder of sexual development that affects males. Males with this disorder have normal male reproductive organs but also have a uterus and uterine tubes.

   Heinrich Müller (1820–1864), Professor of Anatomy, Würzburg, Germany.

Müller–Weiss disease   spontaneous osteonecrosis of the navicular in the adult.

   Walther Müller (1888–1949), German orthopaedic surgeon; Konrad Weiss (1891–1976), Austrian radiologist.

Nabothian cyst, follicle   a retention cyst of the uterine cervix.

   Martin Naboth (1675–1721), Professor of Medicine, Leipzig, Germany.

Newton: Newtonian equations   equations using the SI unit of force (N), which, when applied in a vacuum to a body having a mass of 1 kg, accelerates it at the rate of 1 m/sec^2;

Newton’s second law of motion   applied force=mass×acceleration.

   Sir Isaac Newton (1643–1727), English mathematician and physicist.

Nissl: bodies, granules   basophilic granules in the cytoplasm of neuronal somata;

staining technique   a specific stain for Nissl granules.

   Franz Nissl (1860–1919), neurologist successively at Frankfurt, Heidelberg and Munich, Germany.

Nitabuch’s layer, stria   a layer of fibrinoid matrix between the basal plate of the placenta and the endometrium.

   Raissa Nitabuch, nineteenth-century German physician.

Noonan syndrome   autosomal dominant RASopathy. Clinical features are short stature, low-set ears and minor skeletal deformities of which the commonest are pectus excavatum and cubitus valgus.

   Jacqueline Anne Noonan (1928– ), American paediatric cardiologist.

Nuck, canal of   a diverticulum of the peritoneal membrane extending into the inguinal canal, accompanying the round ligament in the female, or the testis in its descent into the scrotum in the male; usually completely obliterated in the female.

   Anton Nuck (1650–1692), Dutch anatomist.

Nuel, spaces of   spaces between the outer rods of Corti and hair cells.

   Jean Pierre Nuel (1847–1920), Professor of Otology, Louvain and later Liège, Belgium.

Oddi, sphincter of   the sphincter at the termination of the common bile duct. The sphincter had already been described by Glisson (see above) in the seventeenth century.

   Ruggero Oddi (1845–1906), surgeon, Rome, Italy.

Odland bodies   small, lamellated structures (keratinosomes) in the granular layer of the epidermis, containing hydrophobic phospholipid.

   George Fisher Odland (1922–1997), American dermatologist and electron microscopist.

Ondine’s curse   primary alveolar hypoventilation.

   Ondine, a sea nymph in German mythology, who cursed an unfaithful human lover by abolishing the automaticity of his bodily functions.

Onodi cell   a sphenoethmoidal cell formed by lateral and posterior pneumatization of the most posterior ethmoid cells over the sphenoid sinus.

   A Onodi, twentieth-century Hungarian laryngologist.

Onuf, nucleus of   neurones in lamina IX of the sacral spinal cord involved in the maintenance of micturition and defecatory continence.

   Bronislaw Onuf-Onufrowicz (1863–1928), Russian-born American neurologist of Polish descent.

Oort, anastomosis of   a link between the saccular and cochlear nerves at the bottom of the internal auditory meatus (Oort H 1918 Über die Verästelung des Nervus octavus bei Säugetieren (Modell des Utriculus und Sacculus des Kainchens). Anat Anz 851:272–80).

   H Oort, Dutch anatomist, Utrecht.

Oppenheim’s dystonia   Oppenheim described dystonia musculorum deformans (DMD), a movement disorder characterized by twisting or turning movements and abnormal postures. Now called early-onset primary torsion dystonia, this condition is an autosomal dominant disorder most commonly associated with deletion of GAG in the coding region of the DYT1 gene encoding torsinA. It has been suggested that the condition should be referred to as ‘Oppenheim’s dystonia’.

   Hermann Oppenheim (1858–1919), German neurologist.

Osborne, arcuate ligament   otherwise known as the cubital tunnel retinaculum, Osborne’s fascia, Osborne’s band, or the tendinous arch. A band of fibrous tissue that spans between the humeral and ulnar heads of flexor carpi ulnaris and forms the roof of the cubital tunnel.

   Geoffrey Vaughan Osborne (1918–2005), Welsh surgeon.

Osgood–Schlatter disease   osteochondrosis of the tibial tuberosity.

   Robert Bayley Osgood (1873–1956), Professor of Orthopaedic Surgery, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA; Carl Schlatter (1864–1934), Professor of Surgery, Zurich, Switzerland.

Ostmann’s fat pads   two small fat deposits medial and lateral in the membranous part of the Eustachian tube.

   Paul Ostmann (1859–1945), German otologist.

Owen, contour lines of   accentuated incremental lines in the dentine, thought to be due to disturbances in the mineralization process. Defined by parallel deviations of neighbouring dentinal tubules.

   Sir Richard Owen (1804–1892), English anatomist and palaeontologist.

Pacchionian bodies   arachnoid granulations.

   Antoine Pacchion (1665–1726), physician and anatomist, Rome, Italy.

Pacinian corpuscle   a pressure-sensitive mechanoreceptor.

   Filippo Pacini (1812–1883), Professor of Anatomy and Physiology, successively at Pisa and then Florence, Italy.

Paget’s disease   chronic localized disorder of bone remodelling, with increased bone formation and resorption, often resulting in major long-bone and skull deformities.

   Sir James Paget (1814–1899), British surgeon and physiologist.

Palomo procedure   retroperitoneal ligation of the internal spermatic vein between the anterior superior iliac spine and the renal vein (Palomo A 1949 Radical cure of varicocele by a new technique: preliminary report. J Urol 61:604–7).

Pancoast tumour   an apical carcinoma of the lung involving C8 and T1 nerves, the cervical sympathetic chain and upper ribs.

   Henry Pancoast (1875–1939), Professor of Radiology, University of Pennsylvania, USA.

Paneth cells   bacteriocidal lysozyme-secreting cells.

   Joseph Paneth (1857–1890), Professor of Physiology, first at Breslau, Poland, then Vienna, Austria.

Papez circuit   a neuroanatomical circuit mediating emotion, involving the hippocampal formation, mammillary body, anterior nuclei of the thalamus and cingulate gyrus.

   James Wenceslas Papez (1883–1958), American neurologist.

Parkinson’s syndrome, disease   the main symptoms of tremor, rigidity and slowness of movement caused by degeneration of dopaminergic neurones in the substantia nigra, usually occcur in late life and are more common in men.

   James Parkinson (1755–1824), English physician and paleontologist. In his Essay on the Shaking Palsy (1817), Parkinson established the disease that now bears his name as a clinical entity.

Parkinson’s triangle   the infratrochlear triangle. Defined by the inferior margin of the trochlear nerve from its beginning in the lateral wall of the cavernous sinus to its transit through the superior orbital fissure (medial border); the superior margin of the ophthalmic division of the trigeminal nerve (lateral border); and a line connecting the entry points of these nerves into the cavernous sinus (base) (Parkinson D 1965 A surgical approach to the cavernous portion of the carotid artery. Anatomical studies and case report. J Neurosurg 23:474–83).

Parks, mucosal suspensory ligament of   a condensation of fibres at the level of the dentate line (Parks AG 1954 A note on the anatomy of the anal canal. Proc R Soc Med 47:997–8).

Passavant’s: muscle   the upper fibres of palatopharyngeus;

ridge, bar   a projecting ridge, or bar, on the posterior wall of pharynx, which appears during swallowing.

   Phillip Gustav Passavant (1815–1893), surgeon, Frankfurt, Germany.

Petit’s triangle, lumbar triangle of Petit   the inferior lumbar triangle bounded inferiorly by the iliac crest, anteriorly by external oblique and posteriorly by latissimus dorsi.

   Jean L Petit (1640–1750), French surgeon.

Peyer’s patches   lymphoid aggregates in the ileum.

   Johann Conrad Peyer (1653–1712), Professor of Logic, Rhetoric and Medicine in Schaffhausen, Switzerland.

Peyronie’s disease   induration of the corpora cavernosa of the penis, producing a fibrous chordee.

   François de la Peyronie (1678–1747), French surgeon.

Pfannenstiel incision   a transverse curved abdominal incision with downward convexity, above the symphysis pubis.

   Hermann Johann Pfannenstiel (1862–1909), German gynaecologist.

Pfeiffer’s syndrome   a congenital syndrome characterized by craniostenosis, abnormal skull shape, facial anomalies, syndactyly of hands and feet, and broad thumbs and great toes.

   Rudolf Arthur Pfeiffer (1931–2012), human geneticist, Saarbrücken, Germany.

Pierre Robin sequence   micrognathia, U-shaped cleft palate and glossoptosis.

   Pierre Robin (1867–1950), French dentist.

Poirier, space of   a discrete interval between the inferior margin of the fibres of the radioscaphocapitate ligament that attach to the body of the capitate and the palmar horn of the lunate.

   Paul Poirier (1853–1907), French surgeon.

Poiseuille’s law   a mathematical expression of the flow rate for the laminar (nonturbulent) flow of fluids in circular tubes.

   Jean-Louis-Marie Poiseuille (1799–1869), French physician and physiologist.

Poland’s syndrome   a condition that is comprised of ipsilateral breast and nipple hypoplasia and/or aplasia, deficiency of subcutaneous fat and axillary hair, absence of the sternal head of pectoralis major, hypoplasia of the rib cage, and hypoplasia of the upper extremity, including cutaneous syndactyly.

   Sir Alfred Poland (1822–1872), English surgeon.

Poswillo approach   a percutaneous closed reduction technique for management of fractures of the zygoma.

   David Ernest Poswillo (1927–2003), maxillofacial surgeon, New Zealand.

Potter’s syndrome   a rare condition combining a characteristic facial appearance with renal agenesis or hypoplasia and other defects.

   Edith Louise Potter (1901–1993), early twentieth-century American paediatric surgeon.

Pott’s abscess   a tuberculous abscess of the spine.

   Sir Percivall Pott (1713 or 1714–1788), British surgeon.

Prader–Willi syndrome   a rare genetic condition that causes a wide range of physical symptoms, learning difficulties and behavioural problems.

   Andrea Prader (1919–2001), Swiss paediatrician and endocrinologist; Heinrich Willi (1900–1971), Swiss paediatrician.

Pringle manoeuvre   the application of digital or mechanical pressure across the entire free edge of the lesser omentum, resulting in complete, temporary occlusion of the hepatic portal vein, hepatic artery and common bile duct.

   J Pringle the Elder (1863–1941), Australian surgeon.

Prinzmetal’s angina   variant angina occurring at rest, manifesting on electrocardiography as episodic ST segment elevations, and caused by coronary artery spasms with or without superimposed coronary artery disease.

   Myron Prinzmetal (1908–1987), American cardiologist.

Probst, commissure of, Probst bundle   a callosal longitudinal bundle, seen in agenesis of the corpus callosum, when callosal fibres from the hemispheres fail to cross the midline and, instead, form thick bundles.Moriz Probst (1867–1923), Austrian psychiatrist.

Prussak’s: fibres   elastic and connective tissue fibre bounding the pars flaccida membranae tympani;

space   the superior recess of the tympanic membrane.

   Alexander Prussak (1839–1897), Russian otologist.

Purkinje: cells, neurones   large neurones forming a single eponymous layer in the cerebellar cortex;

fibres   subendocardial muscle fibres.

   Johannes Purkinje (1787–1869), Professor of Physiology, Breslau, Poland, and then Prague, Czech Republic.

Ramsay Hunt syndrome   herpes zoster involvement of the geniculate ganglion associated with facial paresis, hyperacusis, unilateral loss of taste, decrease in lacrimation and salivation, and otalgia.

   James Ramsay Hunt (1874–1937), Professor of Neurology, Columbia University, New York, USA.

Ranvier, nodes of   short (∼1 μm) gaps between adjacent myelin sheaths that are essential for the propagation of action potentials via saltatory conduction along myelinated axons.

   Louis-Antoine Ranvier (1835–1922), French anatomist and histopathologist, Paris, France.

Raschkow’s plexus   a plexus of myelinated nerve fibres located between the core of the pulp of the tooth and the cell-rich zone; axons lose their myelin sheath (but not their Schwann cells) as they penetrate the cell-rich and cell-free zones to make synaptic contact with the odontoblast cell body in the pulp or odontoblastic process within the dentinal tubule; responsible for transmitting pain sensation from the pulp of the tooth.

   I Raschkow (1811–1872), German physician.

Rasmussen: bundle of   the olivocochlear tract;

Rasmussen’s encephalitis   a rare, progressive, inflammatory disorder of the central nervous system.

   Theodore Brown Rasmussen (1910–2002), neurologist, Utah, USA.

Rathke’s pouch   a diverticulum of the roof of the stomodeum, which forms the anterior pituitary gland.

   Martin Heinrich Rathke (1793–1860), Professor of Zoology and Anatomy, Königsberg, Germany.

Rayleigh scatter   the scattering of light or other electromagnetic radiation by particles much smaller than the wavelength of the light.

   John William Strutt, 3rd Baron Rayleigh OM (1842–1919), Cavendish Professor of Physics, University of Cambridge, UK.

Raynaud’s disease   idiopathic paroxysmal bilateral cyanosis of the digits due to arterial and arteriolar contraction, caused by cold or emotion.

   Maurice Raynaud (1834–1881), French physician.

Reichert’s cartilage   a cartilage in the mesenchyme of the second branchial arch in the embryo, from which the stapes, styloid processes, stylohyoid ligaments and lesser cornua of the hyoid bone develop.

   Karl Bogislaus Reichert (1811–1883), German anatomist.

Reid’s baseline   a plane that passes through the inferior margin of the orbit and the superior margin of the external acoustic meatus (external auditory canal).

   Robert William Reid (1851–1939), Scottish surgeon and anatomist. He proposed a method of cerebral localization where the topography of the brain could be related to a system of lines drawn between large and easily felt landmarks on the surface of the head.

Reil: circular sulcus of   the peri-insular sulcus (synonym: sulcus circularis insulae); the insular surface is delineated peripherally by the peri-insular sulcus, which is interrupted by the transverse insular gyrus running across the limen insulae;

island of   the insular lobe.

   Johann Christian Reil (1759–1813), German physician.

Reinke’s: crystals   rod-shaped crystals in the interstitial cells of the testis and hilus cells of the ovary;

oedema   chronic laryngitis with swelling of the membranous part of the vocal cords;

space   a potential space between the vocal ligament and the overlying mucosa.

   Friedrich Berthold Reinke (1862–1919), French anatomist.

Reissner’s membrane   the vestibular membrane of the cochlea.

   Ernst Reissner (1824–1878), Professor of Anatomy, Tartu, Estonia, and then Breslau, Poland.

Renshaw’s cells   inhibitory interneurones modulating the response of anterior horn cells.

   Birdsy Renshaw (1911–1948), American neurologist.

Retzius: space of, cave of   the prevesical space or retropubic space;

veins of, retroperitoneal venous plexus of   porto-caval anastomoses formed from veins in the walls of the retroperitoneal viscera, forming communications between the mesenteric veins and the inferior vena cava.

   Andreas Adolf Retzius (1796–1860), Professor of Anatomy, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden.

Retzius: cell   see Cajal–Retzius cell;

gyrus   two small bulges on the medial segment of the hippocampal tail that consist of a CA1 subfield and the subiculum (Ziogas IA, Triarhou L 2016 Anders Retzius and his gyri. Neurol Sci 37:1861–6);

inferior sagittal sulcus of the cuneus of   a structure that lies superior to the posterior part of the calcarine sulcus;

lines of, striae of   brown lines in the dental enamel;

superior sagittal sulcus of   a paracalcarine sulcus (Retzius G 1896 Das Menschenhirn. Königliche Buchdruckerei PA Norstedt und Söner, Stockholm).

   Gustav Magnus Retzius (1842–1919), Professor of Anatomy, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden. Son of Andreas Adolf Retzius.

Rexed’s lamina   subdivisions of cells of spinal cord grey matter.

   Bror Rexed (1914–2002), Swedish neuroanatomist.

Riolan, arc of   the anastomosis between the middle and left colic arteries.

   Jean Riolan (Secondus) (1577–1657), Professor of Anatomy and Botany, Paris, France.

Rives–Stoppa–Wantz technique   a technique that involves incising the posterior layer of the rectus sheath just lateral to the linea alba, allowing a retromuscular dissection to the lateral edge of the rectus sheath.

   Jean Rives (1922–2012), Rene Stoppa (1921–2006), French-Algerian surgeons; George E. Wantz (1923–2000), American surgeon.

Rolando: cruciform sulcus of   the H-shaped orbital sulcus;

Rolandic fissure   the central fissure of the cerebral hemisphere.

   Luigi Rolando (1773–1831), Italian anatomist.

Romberg sign   swaying of the body or falling when standing with the feet close together and the eyes closed.

   Moritz Heinrich Romberg (1795–1873), German physician.

Rosenmüller, fossa of   the pharyngeal recess.

   Johann Christian Rosenmüller (1779–1820), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Leipzig, Germany.

Rosenthal: basal vein of   a vein that courses from the premesencephalic cistern, through the ambient cistern, and terminates in the quadrigeminal cistern;

Rosenthal’s canal   the spiral canal in the modiolus of the cochlea.

   Isidor Rosenthal (1836–1915), physiologist, Greifswald, Germany.

Roser–Nelaton’s line   a line drawn from the anterior superior iliac spine to the ischial tuberosity.

   Auguste Nélaton (1807–1873), French physician and surgeon; Wilhelm Roser (1817–1888), German surgeon and ophthalmologist.

Rotter’s node   the lymph node between pectoralis major and minor.

   Josef Rotter (1857–1924), German surgeon.

Rouvière’s sulcus   the incisura hepatis dextra (synonym: Gans incisura) (see Stringer MD 2009 Eponyms in Surgery and Anatomy of the Liver, Bile Ducts and Pancreas. London: Royal Society of Medicine).

Ruffini endings, bodies, corpuscles   sensory nerve endings, originally described in the skin of the fingers.

   Angelo Ruffini (1887–1929), Professor of Histology, Bologna, Italy.

Russell, hook bundle of   uncinate fasciculus, where the crossed fibres from the fastigial nucleus pass dorsal to the superior cerebellar peduncle.

   James Samuel Risien Russell (1863–1939), Guyanese-British neurologist.

Sachs, sagittal striata of   extrastriate thalamocortical projections (internal sagittal stratum of Sachs); association fibres of the inferior longitudinal fasciculus (external sagittal stratum of Sachs).

   Heinrich Sachs (1863–1928), German neurologist and a student of Carl Wernicke in Breslau.

Saethre–Chotzen syndrome   acrocephalosyndactyly type III. A very rare disorder characterized by the fusion of cranial structures, which sometimes produces an asymmetric head and face; low-set hairline; ptosis and/or widely spaced eyes; ‘beaked’ nose and possible deviated septum; and, sometimes, brachydactyly and syndactyly.

   Haakon Saethre (1891–1945), Norwegian psychiatrist; F. Chotzen (1932), German psychiatrist.

Santorini: duct of   the accessory pancreatic duct;

fissures of   two fissures in the anterior cartilaginous wall of the external acoustic meatus;

plexus of   the retropubic venous plexus giving rise to the pudendal vein.

   Giovanni Domenico Santorini (1681–1737), Professor of Medicine and Anatomy, Venice, Italy.

Satiro’s ear   usually known as Stahl’s syndrome or Satyr’s ear. A common congenital deformity of the auricle in which the helix is flattened and the upper crus of the antihelix is duplicated.

   Friedrich Stahl (1811–1879), German physician.

Sattler’s layer   a layer of medium-sized blood vessels in the choroid, derived from the short posterior ciliary arteries.

   Hubert Sattler (1844–1928), Professor of Ophthalmology, Leipzig University Eye Hospital, Germany.

Scarpa’s: fascia   the fibrous layer of the superficial fascia of the lower abdomen;

ganglion   the vestibular ganglion.

   Antonio Scarpa (1747–1832), Professor of Anatomy, Padua, Italy.

Schaffer collaterals   the projections from pyramidal cells of fields CA3 and CA2 to CA1 in the hippocampus.

   Max Schaffer (1852–1923), German neurologist.

Scheuermann’s osteochondritis, disease, kyphosis   osteochondrosis of the vertebrae.

   Holger Werfel Scheuermann (1834–1915), German biochemist.

Schiff’s stain, reagent   a stain for aldehydes, used with periodic acid (PAS) to detect carbohydrates.

   Hugo Schiff (1834–1915), German biochemist.

Schirmer test   a test that measures lacrimal gland secretory capacity; used principally to diagnose dry eye syndrome.

   Otto Schirmer (1864–1918), German ophthalmologist.

Schlemm, canal of   a canal at the junction of the cornea and sclera.

   Freidrich Schlemm (1795–1858), Professor of Anatomy, Berlin, Germany.

Schmidt–Lanterman incisures, cleft   a helical inclusion of glial cytoplasm within the myelin sheaths of central and peripheral nerves.

   Henry Schmidt (1823–1888), pathologist, Charity Hospital, New Orleans, USA; AJ Lanterman, nineteenth-century anatomist, Strasbourg, France.

Schütz, fasciculus of   the dorsal longitudinal fasciculus.

   Hugo Schütz (1859–1923), neurologist, Leipzig, Germany.

Schwalbe: line of, ring of   the anterior border ring of the cornea;

nucleus of   the vestibular nucleus;

pocket   a depression between the tendinous arch of levator ani and the lateral wall of the pelvis.

   Gustav Albert Schwalbe (1844–1916), German anatomist and anthropologist.

Schwann cell   the major glial cell of the peripheral nervous system.

   Theodor Schwann (1810–1882), Professor of Anatomy first in Louvain and then Liège, Belgium. One of the instigators of the cell theory.

Seessel’s pouch   a small endodermal diverticulum that projects towards the brain from the cranial end of the foregut, immediately caudal to the buccopharyngeal membrane.

   Albert Seessel (1850–1910), American embryologist.

Segond fracture   an avulsion fracture of the lateral margin of the lateral tibial plateau, with a significant association with anterior cruciate ligament and meniscal injuries.

   Paul Ferdinand Segond (1851–1912), French orthopaedic surgeon.

Semon’s law   an obsolete ‘law’ stating that injury to the recurrent laryngeal nerve results in paralysis of the abductor muscles of the vocal cords before paralysis of the adductor muscles.

   Sir Felix Semon (1849–1921), German laryngologist in the UK.

Sertoli cells   the supporting cells of the testicular tubules.

   Enrico Sertoli (1842–1910), Professor of Experimental Physiology, Milan, Italy.

Sever’s disease   inflammation of the calcaneal apophysis in children and adolescents.James Warren Sever (1878–1964), American orthopaedic surgeon.

Sharpey’s fibres   connective tissue joining periosteum to bone.

   William Sharpey (1802–1880), Professor of Anatomy successively at Edinburgh and University College, London, UK.

Sibson’s fascia   the suprapleural membrane.

   Francis Sibson (1814–1846), English surgeon.

Simmonds–Thompson test   a diagnostic tool for Achilles tendon rupture: absence of foot plantar flexion on calf compression is interpreted as a positive test result.

   Franklin Adin Simmonds (1910–1983), English orthopaedic surgeon; Theodore Campbell Thompson (1902–1986), American orthopaedic surgeon.

Sistrunk’s procedure   a procedure for removal of a thyroglossal duct cyst. It involves resection of the entire cyst, the central portion of the hyoid bone, and the thyroglossal duct tract that terminates at the foramen caecum. Several modifications of the procedure have been described.

   Walter Ellis Sistrunk (1880–1933), American surgeon; originally described this operation in 1920.

Sjögren’s connective tissue disease   a chronic autoimmune disease characterized by keratoconjunctivitis sicca and many other symptoms.

   Henrik Samuel Conrad Sjögren (1899–1986), Swedish ophthalmologist.

Skene’s glands   the paraurethral ducts of the female urethra.

   Alexander Johnston Chalmers Skene (1838–1900), gynaecologist, New York, USA.

Skoog, fibres of   transverse fibres of the palmar aponeurosis of the hand.

   Tord Skoog (1915–1977), Foundation Professor of Plastic Surgery, University of Uppsala, Sweden.

Sly syndrome   mucopolysaccharidosis type VII (MPS-VII), an autosomal recessive lysosomal storage disease caused by a deficiency of β-glucuronidase.

   William S Sly (1932– ), American physician.

Sondergaard   see Waterston, groove of.

   Tyge Sondergaard (1914–1990), Danish cardiac surgeon. The first surgeon to use cold chemical cardioplegia in open heart surgery.

Spence, tail of   the projection of mammary glandular tissue extending into the axillary region, sometimes forming a visible mass that may enlarge premenstrually or during lactation.

   James Spence (1812–1882), Scottish surgeon.

Spiegel, Spigelian, Spieghel: hernia   (1–2% of all hernias – the protrusion of extraperitoneal fat, peritoneal sac or organ(s) through a congenital or acquired defect in the Spiegelian aponeurosis (i.e. the aponeurosis of transversus abdominis limited by the semilunar line laterally and the lateral edge of rectus muscle medially). Although named after Adriaan van der Spieghel, the semilunar line (linea Spiegeli) was only described by Spieghel in 1645. Josef Klinkosch first defined the Spiegelian hernia as a defect in the semilunar line in 1764. Defects in the aponeurosis of transversus abdominis (mainly distal to the arcuate line and more often in obese individuals) have been considered the principal aetiological factor;

line   the linea semilunaris (semilunar line);

lobe   the caudate lobe of the liver.

   Adriaan van den Spiegel (1578–1625), Flemish anatomist and botanist. Name also written as Spieghel, Spigel, Adrianus Spigelius, Spiegelius, Adriano Spigeli.

Sprengel deformity   congenital elevation of the scapula with rotation of its lower angle towards the spine.

   Otto Gerhard Karl Sprengel (1852–1915), German surgeon.

Stahl’s deformity   congenital deformity of the ear characterised by a broad helix, absence of the fossa of the antihelix and upper scaphoid fossa.

   Friedrich Stahl (1811–1879), German physician.

Stanford classification   a widely used system of classifying aortic dissections first proposed by a group of cardiovascular surgeons at Stanford University, in which dissections that involve the ascending aorta are classified as type A, regardless of the site of the primary intimal tear, and all other dissections as type B (Daily PO, Trueblood HW, Stinson EB et al 1970 Management of acute aortic dissections. Ann Thorac Surg 10:237–47).

Stener lesion   the ulnar collateral ligament is normally covered by the aponeurotic fibres of the tendon of adductor pollicis. Following avulsion, the proximal end of the ligament can become superficially displaced around the proximal free edge of the aponeurotic insertion of adductor pollicis, producing a Stener lesion (Stener B 1962 Displacement of the ruptured ulnar collateral ligament of the metacarpo-phalangeal joint of the thumb. J Bone Joint Surg Br 44:869–79).

   Bertil Stener, Swedish orthopaedic surgeon.

Sternberg’s canal   otherwise known as the lateral craniopharyngeal canal. Originally described as a membranous space in the lateral wall of the sphenoid sinus, this rare small canal was once believed to be the primary cause of spontaneous lateral sphenoid CSF leaks.

   Maximilian Sternberg (1863–1934), Austrian physician.

Stickler syndrome   hereditary progressive arthro-ophthalmodystrophy, characterized by a distinctive flattened facial appearance, numerous ocular abnormalities, sensorineural or conductive hearing loss, and skeletal abnormalities that affect the joints.

   Gunnar B Stickler (1925–2010), German paediatrician.

Stieda’s process   the lateral tubercle of the talus, when elongated.

   Christian Hermann Ludwig Stieda (1837–1918), German anatomist.

Struthers: arcade of   a thickening of the anteromedial aspect of the medial intermuscular septum, forming a myofibrous sheath around the ulnar nerve after it passes from the anterior to the posterior compartment of the arm;

ligament of   a ligamentous or muscular structure (often an extension of the humeral head of pronator teres), passing between the medial epicondyle and supracondylar processes of the humerus in approximately 1% of individuals.

   Sir John Struthers (1823–1899), Scottish anatomist, professor and surgeon.

Sylvian: aqueduct   the midbrain channel connecting the third and fourth cerebral ventricles;

cistern   the subarachnoid space associated with the lateral cerebral sulcus (Sylvian fissure). It contains the M1 segment of the middle cerebral artery, the origin of the lenticulostriate arteries, and proximal parts of the middle cerebral artery;

fissure   the lateral cerebral fissure;

vein   the superficial middle cerebral vein.

   François de la Boe Sylvius (1614–1672), Professor of Medicine, Leiden, Netherlands.

Takayasu’s arteritis   a granulomatous vasculitis with massive intimal fibrosis and vascular narrowing mainly affecting the aorta and its large branches (aka aortic arch syndrome, nonspecific aortoarteritis, pulseless disease).

   Mikito Takayasu (1860–1938), Japanese ophthalmologist.

Tamm–Horsfall protein   the most abundant protein in normal urine.

   Igor Tamm (1922–1995), virologist, New York, USA; Frank Lappin Horsfall (1906–1971), American clinician and virologist.

Tanner’s stages   scales for stages of sexual development in puberty.

   James Mourilyan Tanner (1920–2010), British paediatric endocrinologist.

Taussig–Bing anomaly, syndrome, disease   transposition of the aorta to the right ventricle and malposition of the pulmonary artery with subpulmonary ventricular septal defect.

   Helen B Taussig (1898–1986), American paediatrician; Richard Bing (1909–2010), American physician.

Tay–Sachs disease   a lysosomal storage disorder affecting neurones.

   Warren Tay (1843–1927), ophthalmologist, London, UK; Bernard Sachs (1858–1944), neurologist, New York, USA.

Tenon’s capsule   the fascial sheath of the eyeball.

   Jacques René Tenon (1724–1816), Professor of Pathology, Academy of Sciences, Paris. Chief Surgeon, Salpêtrière, Paris, France. Specialized in ophthalmology.

Testut, ligament of   a radio-scaphoid-lunate connection.

   Leo Testut (1849–1925), Professor of Anatomy, Lyons, France.

Thebesian: valve   the valve at the orifice of the coronary sinus;

veins   venae cordis minimae of the heart.

   Adam Christian Thebesius (1686–1732), anatomist and pathologist, Leiden, Netherlands.

Thomine, retrovascular cord of   a pathological cord formed from the retrovascular fascia or band of Thomine (longitudinally oriented fibres dorsal to the neurovascular bundle) (Thomine JM 1985 The development and anatomy of the digital fascia. In: Hueston JT, Tubiana R eds, Dupuytren’s Disease, 2nd ed. New York: Churchill Livingstone, pp. 3–12).

Thompson, posterior (dorsal) approach of   a surgical approach to treat fractures of the proximal and middle thirds of the radius and to address injury to the proximal radioulnar joint (Thompson JE 1918 Anatomical methods of approach in operations on the long bones or extremities. Ann Surg 68:309–29).

Thornwaldt cyst   a benign cyst located in the upper posterior nasopharynx, covered by mucosa anteriorly and bounded by longus muscles posteriorly.

   Gustav Ludwig Tornwaldt/Thornwaldt (1843–1910), German physician.

Tinel’s sign   the fact that lightly tapping (percussing) over a nerve trunk that has been damaged or is regenerating following trauma causes a sensation of tingling and pain in its distribution up to the site of regeneration. In closed injuries, percussion of the skin over a nerve in which axons have been ruptured evokes sensations that are usually described as a wave or surge of pins and needles into the cutaneous distribution of the nerve.

   Jules Tinel (1879–1952), French neurologist.

Todaro, tendon of   a variable tendinous strand attached to the valvular fold at the termination of the inferior vena cava. It forms the superior border of the triangle of Koch.

   Francesco Todaro (1839–1918), Professor of Anatomy at Messina and then Rome, Italy.

Toldt’s fascia, fusion fascia of Toldt   an avascular fascial plane posterior to the ascending or descending colon and mesocolon, kidney and tail of the pancreas.

   Carl Toldt (1840–1920), Austrian anatomist.

Towne’s projection   positioning of the head in the radiological examination of the foramen magnum and posterior cranial fossa.

   Edward Towne (1883–1957), neurosurgeon, Stanford Medical School, California, USA.

Treacher Collins syndrome   mandibulofacial dysostosis.

   Edward Treacher Collins (1862–1932), English surgeon.

Treitz: fascia of, fusion fascia of   the fascia behind the head of the pancreas;

ligament of   a fold of peritoneum over the suspensory muscle of the duodenum;

muscle of   the suspensory muscle of the duodenum (musculus suspensorius duodenii).

   Václav (Wenzel) Treitz (1819–1872), Professor of Pathological Anatomy, Jagellonian University, Prague, Czech Republic.

Trendelenburg’s sign, gait   a dipping gait due to hip abductor dysfunction, e.g. in congenital dislocation of the hip or paralysis of gluteus medius and minimus.

   Friedrich Trendelenburg (1844–1924), Professor of Surgery successively at Rostock, Bonn and Leipzig, Germany.

Treves, bloodless fold of   a peritoneal fold adjacent to the mesoappendix.

   Sir Frederick Treves (1853–1923), surgeon, London Hospital, UK. Drained the appendicular abscess of King Edward VII in 1902.

Trolard: canal of   the sphenoparietal canal: a short bony canal that contains the anterior branches of the middle meningeal vessels;

superior anastomotic vein of   the vein that connects the superior sagittal sinus and the superficial middle cerebral vein (of Sylvius).

   Paulin Trolard (1842–1910), French anatomist.

Tsai, ventral tegmental area of   the ventral tegmental area.

   Tsai Chiao (1897–1990), Chinese physiologist.

Tuffier’s line   a line that may be drawn between the highest points of the iliac crests on which the spine of L4 usually lies in adults.

   Théodore Tuffier (1857–1929), French surgeon.

Türk, bundle of   corticopontine fibres that originate from parietal, occipital and temporal lobes.

   Ludwig Türck (1810–68), Austrian neurologist.

Turner syndrome   a disorder of gonadal differentiation, marked by short stature, undifferentiated (streak) gonads and variable anomalies that may include webbing of the neck, low posterior hair line and cardiac defects.

   Henry Hubert Turner (1892–1970), American endocrinologist.

Twining’s line   the line between the tuberculum sellae and the torcular.

   Edward Wing Twining (1887–1939), often cited as the ‘father of British neuroradiology’.

Urbach–Wiethe syndrome   lipoid proteinosis, an autosomal recessive multisystem genodermatosis that primarily affects the skin, oral cavity and larynx, with the deposition of an amorphous hyaline material as a consequence of mutation of extracellular matrix protein 1 (ECM1). Neurological complications include basal ganglia calcification, usually bilaterally symmetrical.

   Erich Urbach (1893–1946), Austrian dermatologist; Camillo Wiethe (1889–1949), Austrian otorhinolaryngologist.

Usher syndrome, Usher–Hallgren syndrome   a condition characterized by hearing loss or deafness and progressive loss of vision caused by retinitis pigmentosa. The three major types of Usher syndrome (types I, II and III) are distinguished by their severity and the age at which signs and symptoms appear (synonyms: Hallgren syndrome, dysacusis syndrome, dystrophia retinae dysacusis syndrome).

   Charles Howard Usher (1865–1942), Scottish ophthalmologist.

Valoean sheath   the connective tissue capsule surrounding the liver.

   Valoeus, an anatomist from the Middle Ages, who first described the liver capsule.

Valsalva: aortic sinuses of   the aortic sinuses;

manoeuvre   any forced expiratory effort (‘strain’) against a closed airway, whether at the nose and mouth or at the glottis.

   Antonio Maria Valsalva (1666–1723), Professor of Anatomy, Bologna, Italy.

van de Woude’s syndrome   an autosomal dominant syndrome characterized by a cleft lip or cleft palate, and/or distinctive pits of the lower lips, the most common syndrome associated with cleft lip or cleft palate (Van der Woude A 1954 Fistula labii inferioris congenita and its association with cleft lip and palate. Am J Hum Genet 6:244–56).

van Gieson technique, elastic van Gieson technique   a solution of trinitrophenol and acid fuchsin used to stain connective tissue elastin on histological sections.

   Ira Thompson van Gieson (1866–1913), American neuropathologist, New York, USA.

Vater, ampulla of   the ampulla at the junction of the common hepatic and pancreatic ducts.

   Abraham Vater (1684–1751), Professor of Anatomy, Botany, Pathology and Therapeutics, Wittenburg, Germany.

Velpeau, space of   (quadrangular space, quadrilateral space, foramen humerotricipitale): a space bounded by subscapularis, the capsule of the shoulder joint and teres minor superiorly, teres major inferiorly, the long head of triceps medially and the surgical neck of the humerus laterally. The axillary nerve and the posterior circumflex humeral artery and vein pass obliquely through the space.

   Alfred-Armand-Louis-Marie Velpeau (1795–1867), French anatomist and surgeon.

Vesalius, foramen of   a small foramen for the emissary vein immediately anterior and medial to the foramen ovale in the sphenoid bone.

   Andreas Vesalius (1514–1564), Professor of Anatomy, Padua, Italy.

Vicq d’Azyr, band or stripe of   a white band or stripe in the occipital cortex; also described by Gennari in 1782.

   Félix Vicq d’Azyr (1748–94), French physician, anatomist, historian and social reformer who is often described as the greatest comparative anatomist of the eighteenth century before Cuvier.

Vidian: canal   the pterygoid canal;

nerve   the nerve of the pterygoid canal.

   Guido Guidi Vidius (1500–1561), Professor of Medicine, Pisa, Italy.

Vieussens: anulus of   the ansa subclavia of sympathetic nerves; a tenuous anastomosis around the right ventricular outflow tract

arterial ring   an inconstant anastomosis around the right ventricular outflow tract that may provide an important collateral circulation in cases of arterial occlusion.

   Raymond de Vieussens (1641–1715), physician and anatomist, Montpellier, France.

Virchow–Robin space   a perivascular space in the central nervous system.

   Rudolf Ludwig Virchow (1821–1902), Professor of Pathological Anatomy, Würzburg, and then Berlin, Germany; Charles-Philippe Robin (1821–1885), Professor of Histology, Paris, France.

Vogt, palisades of   crests of epithelial folds at the limbus that run radially towards the cornea from the bulbar conjunctiva.

   Alfred Vogt (1879–1943), Swiss ophthalmologist.

Voigt’s lines, Voigt–Futcher lines   pigmentary demarcation lines or hair tracts (synonym: Futcher’s lines).

   Christian August Voigt (1809–1890), Professor of Anatomy, Vienna, Austria; Palmer Howard Futcher (1910–2004), US–Canadian physician.

Volkmann’s: canals   osseous canals carrying blood vessels from the periosteum and between osteons;

ischaemic contracture   a permanent flexion contracture of the hand at the wrist, resulting in a claw-like deformity of the hand and fingers.

   Alfred Wilhelm Volkmann (1800–1877), Professor of Anatomy and Physiology, first at Dorpat, Estonia, and later Halle, Germany.

von Brunn’s nests   ectopic (subepithelial) urothelial masses in the urinary tract.

   Albert von Brunn (1849–1872), Professor of Anatomy, Göttingen, Germany.

von Ebner’s: fissure   in the development of the back, sclerotomal populations form from the ventral half of the epithelial somite. An intrasegmental boundary (fissure or cleft, sometimes termed von Ebner’s fissure), which is initially filled with extracellular matrix and a few cells, appears within the sclerotome and divides it into loosely packed cranial, and densely packed caudal, halves;

glands   serous glands of the tongue, located beneath the circumvallate and foliate papillae;

lines   incremental lines of dentine.

   Anton Gilbert Viktor von Ebner (also commonly called Viktor von Ebner-Rofenstein) (1842–1925), Professor of Histology and Embryology, Innsbruck, Austria.

Von Economo neurone   spindle neurone characterized by a single apical dendrite, a single basal dendrite and a long projection axon.

   Constantin von Economo (1876–1931), Austrian psychiatrist and neurologist.

von Hippel–Lindau disease   an autosomal dominant genetic condition with high penetrance resulting from a deletion or mutation in the VHL tumour suppressor gene on chromosome 3p25.3. Characterized by retinal and CNS haemangioblastomas, pheochromocytomas, multiple cysts in the pancreas and kidneys. Benign tumours have an increased potential for malignant transformation.

   Eugen Adolf Arthur von Hippel (1867–1939), German ophthalmologist; Arvid Vilhelm Lindau (1892–1958), Swedish pathologist and bacteriologist.

von Willebrand factor   the factor released from endothelial cells and platelets, promoting platelet adhesion and blood clotting. Deficient or defective factor production (usually inherited as an autosomal dominant trait) causes von Willebrand disease.

   Erik Adolf von Willebrand (1870–1949), Finnish haematologist. Described the eponymous hereditary clotting disorder in 1926.

Waardenburg type II syndrome   a deafness syndrome associated with pigmentary disturbances. A group of heterogeneous entities distinguished from Waardenburg type I syndrome by the absence of dystopia canthorum.

   Petrus Johannes Waardenburg (1886–1979), Dutch ophthalmologist and geneticist.

Waldeyer: presacral fascia of   the floor of the retrorectal space (Jin ZM, Peng JY, Zhu QC et al 2011 Waldeyer’s fascia: anatomical location and relationship to neighboring fasciae in retrorectal space. Surg Radiol Anat 33:851–4);

Waldeyer’s ring   a ring of lymphoid tissue that includes the palatine, pharyngeal, tubal and lingual tonsils;

Waldeyer’s sheath   adventitia of distal segments of the ureter.

   Heinrich Wilhelm Waldeyer (1836–1921), Professor of Pathology at Breslau, Poland, and then Berlin, Germany.

Wallenberg’s syndrome   a lesion of the lateral medullary region of the brainstem.

   Adolf Wallenberg (1862–1949), German physician.

Wallerian degeneration   degeneration of myelinated and unmyelinated axons distal to any injury that transects the axons and separates their distal segments from their centrally placed neuronal cell bodies.

   Augustus Volney Waller (1816–1870), British neurophysiologist.

Walther, ganglion of   the solitary, retroperitoneal median ganglion impar or sacrococcygeal ganglion, which lies anterior to the sacrococcygeal junction; it represents the distal termination of the sympathetic chains.

   August F Walther (1688–1746), German anatomist.

Wartenberg’s disease, sign, symptom   radial sensory nerve entrapment.

   Robert Wartenberg (1866–1956), American neurologist.

Warwick’s foramen   a foramen located between the inferior end of the superior orbital fissure and the foramen rotundum.

   Roger Warwick (1912–1991), English anatomist.

Waterston, groove of/interatrial sulcus of   the sulcus separating the right and left atria of the heart (aka Sondergaard’s groove).

   David Waterston (1910–1985), Scottish cardiothoracic surgeon.

Weigert–Meyer rule   the rule that, when complete, duplicated ureters insert separately into the bladder; the upper pole ureter is the ectopic ureter and its orifice inserts inferomedially in the bladder; the lower pole ureter is the normal ureterCarl Weigert (1845–1904), German pathologist; Robert Meyer(1864–1947), German gynaecologist and pathologist.

Weigert, staining technique of   histological stains for myelin and for elastic fibres. The former uses a solution of ferric chloride and haematoxylin that stains myelin sheaths deep blue and degenerated tissue a pale yellow; the latter uses a resorcin–fuchsin solution that stains elastic fibres blue–black.

   Carl Weigert (1845–1904), German histopathologist, Frankfurt-am-Main, Germany.

Werner’s syndrome   a rare, autosomal recessive progeroid syndrome, characterized by the appearance of premature ageing.

   Carl Wilhelm Otto Werner (1879–1936), German physician.

Wernicke: frontomarginal sulcus of   frontomarginal sulcus in the cerebral cortex;

Wernicke’s speech area   the motor speech area in the superior temporal lobe of the cerebral cortex;

Wernicke’s syndrome   a syndrome characterized by mental and ocular disorders and ataxia. Mental disturbances include listlessness, disorientation, confusion, hallucinations, Korsakoff psychosis and other behavioural symptoms.

   Karl (or Carl) Wernicke (1848–1904), German physician, anatomist, psychiatrist and neuropathologist. Breslau, Poland, and then Halle, Germany.

Wharton’s: duct   a duct of the submandibular salivary gland;

jelly   a homogenous intercellular substance of the umbilical cord; gives a reaction for mucin and contains thin collagenous fibres that increase in number with fetal age.

   Thomas Wharton (1614–1673), physician and anatomist, St Thomas’s Hospital, London, UK. Remained on duty there during the Great Plague of 1665.

Whipple procedure   pancreaticoduodenectomy.

   Allen Oldfather Whipple (1881–1963), American surgeon.

Whitnall: transverse ligament of   a ligament that originates from the trochlea and inserts into the lateral orbital wall, approximately 10 mm above Whitnall’s tubercle;

Whitnall’s tubercle   a tubercle on the orbital surface of the zygomatic bone.

   Samuel Ernest Whitnall (1876–1950), Professor of Anatomy, successively at McGill University, Montreal, Canada, and Bristol, UK.

Wiebel–Palade bodies   rod-shaped storage granules in endothelial cells.

   Euald Wiebel, Swiss physician; George Emil Palade (1912–2008), Romanian cytologist, Rockefeller Institute, New York, USA, awarded the Nobel Prize for Medicine or Physiology in 1974.

Williams–Campbell syndrome   a rare form of congenital cystic bronchiectasis, in which distal bronchial cartilage is defective (Williams H, Campbell P 1960 Generalized bronchiectasis associated with deficiency of cartilage in the bronchial tree. Arch Dis Child 35:182–91).

   Howard Williams, twentieth-century Australian physician; Peter E Campbell, twentieth-century Australian physician.

Willis, circle of   circulus arteriosus cerebri (cerebral arterial circle); the arterial anastomosis at the base of the brain.

   Thomas Willis (1621–1675), physician to King James II, practised first in Oxford, then London, UK.

Wilson’s pencils, pencil fibres of Wilson   the striatopallidal fibres (Wilson SAK 1914 An experimental research into the anatomy and physiology of the corpus striatum. Brain 36:427–92).

   Samuel Kinnier Wilson (1878–1937), American-born British neurologist.

Winslow, foramen of   the epiploic foramen leading to the lesser sac.

   Jacob B Winslow (1669–1760), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery, Paris, France.

Wirsung, duct of   the main pancreatic duct.

   Johann Georg Wirsung (1589–1643), German physician, Prosector in Anatomy, Padua, Italy.

Wiskott–Aldrich syndrome   primary immunodeficiency resulting from an X-linked recessive mutation.

   Alfred Wiskott (1898–1978), German paediatrician; Robert Anderson Aldrich (1917–1998), American paediatrician.

Wolffian: body   the mesonephros;

duct   the mesonephric duct.

   Caspar Wolff (1733–1794), born in Berlin, Professor of Anatomy, St Petersburg, Russia, one of the pioneers of embryology.

Wolff’s law   states that changes in the stresses on bones are reflected in their internal structure.

   Julius Wolff (1836–1902), orthopaedic surgeon, Berlin, Germany.

Wolff–Parkinson–White syndrome   bundle-branch block with short P–R interval in healthy young people prone to paroxysmal tachycardia.

   Louis Wolff (1898–1972), American cardiologist; John Parkinson (1885–1976), English cardiologist; Paul Dudley White (1886–1973), American cardiologist.

Wolfring, glands of   small tubuloalveolar glands in the subconjunctival tissue above the upper border of the tarsal plate.

   Emilij Franzevic von Wolfring (1832–1906), Polish ophthalmologist.

Wormian bones   small bones that occasionally occur along the lambdoid suture of the human skull (synonym: sutural bones).

   Ole Worm (1588–1654), physician, Professor of Medicine, University of Copenhagen, Denmark.

Wright’s stain   a mixture of eosin and methylene blue, used for demonstrating blood corpuscles and malarial parasites on histological sections or blood smears.

   James Homer Wright (1869–1928), pathologist, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.

Wrisberg, ligament of   a band attached to the posterior cruciate ligament of the knee.

   Heinrich August Wrisberg (1739–1808), Professor of Anatomy, Göttingen, Germany.

Yakovlev’s circuit   one of the divisions of the limbic system, a circuit involving the orbitofrontal, insular and anterior temporal lobe cortex, the amygdala and the dorsomedial nucleus of the thalamus, involved in emotion, reward and social behaviour.

   Paul Ivan Yakovlev (1894–1983), Russian-born neurologist and neuropathologist who worked in the USA from 1925.

Young’s modulus   sometimes called Young’s modulus of elasticity: a measure of the ability of a material to withstand changes in length when under lengthwise tension or compression.

   Thomas Young (1773–1829), British physician and physicist.

Zeis, glands of   modified rudimentary sebaceous glands attached directly to the follicles of the eyelashes.

   Edward Zeis (1807–1868), German ophthalmologist.

Zellweger’s syndrome   an inherited defect in peroxisome biogenesis and functioning.

   Hans Ulrich Zellweger (1909–1990), Swiss–American paediatrician.

Zencker’s diverticulum   a posteromedial pulsion diverticulum through Killian’s dehiscence that causes debilitating dysphagia and regurgitation.

   Friedrich Albert von Zenker (1825–1898), German physician and pathologist.

Zinn: anulus of   otherwise known as the common tendinous ring, it is a fibrous ring that surrounds the optic canal and part of the superior orbital fissure at the apex of the orbit and gives origin to the four recti;

circle of, zonula of   an (often incomplete) vascular circle within the sclera, formed by branches of the short posterior ciliary arteries, whose centripetal branches supply the laminar region of the optic nerve head (synonym: circle of Haller, zonula of Haller).

   Johann Gottfried Zinn (1727–1759), Professor of Medicine and Director of Botanical Gardens, Göttingen, Germany.

Zuckerkandl: fascia of   the fascia posterior or anterior to the kidney;

organ of   the para-aortic bodies (also known as paraganglia) are collections of neural crest-derived chromaffin tissue found in close relation to the abdominal aortic plexus;

tuberculum of, tubercle of   a projection of normal thyroid tissue from the posterior or lateral lobes of the thyroid gland.

   Emil Zuckerkandl (1849–1910), Professor of Anatomy at Graz and then Vienna, Austria.

Many of the eponyms in this list are described in more detail in Firkin BG, Whitworth JA 2001 Dictionary of Medical Eponyms. London: Parthenon. A concise illustrated account of the derivation and individuals behind the more common eponyms associated with liver anatomy and surgery is provided in Stringer MD 2009 Eponyms in Surgery and Anatomy of the Liver, Bile Ducts and Pancreas. London: Royal Society of Medicine.